<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Whaddon in Buckinghamshyre the 22. of Nouember 1593. at the buriall of the Right Honorable, Arthur Lorde Grey of Wilton, Knight of the most Honorable order of the Garter, by Thomas Sparke pastor of Blechley</title>
            <author>Sparke, Thomas, 1548-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838216</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2583</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2583)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1085:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Whaddon in Buckinghamshyre the 22. of Nouember 1593. at the buriall of the Right Honorable, Arthur Lorde Grey of Wilton, Knight of the most Honorable order of the Garter, by Thomas Sparke pastor of Blechley</title>
                  <author>Sparke, Thomas, 1548-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes printer to the Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2583:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2583:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT WHADDON in Buckinghamſhyre the 22. of Nouember <hi>1593.</hi> at the buriall of the Right Honorable, ARTHVR Lorde <hi>GREY</hi> of Wilton, Knight of the moſt Honorable order of the Garter, by THOMAS SPARKE Paſtor of Blechley.</p>
            <p>AT OXFORD, Printed by IOSEPH BARNES Printer to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</p>
            <p>1593.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2583:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2583:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, <hi>AND HIS VERY GOOD LADIES,</hi> the Counteſſe of BEDFORD, and the Ladie GREY <hi>her Honours Daughter, and to the</hi> Right honorable, THOMAS, Lord GREY of <hi>Wilton, his very good Lord; Thomas Sparke</hi> wiſheth all neceſſary ſpirituall bleſſings, in Chriſt Ieſus, with health &amp; al proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity to their own full contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and comfort.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE the preaching of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon following (Right honorable) J know, you are not ignorant, how ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly I haue beene requeſted, to publiſh the ſame in Print: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering therefore, that therin, there was ſet before vs in that Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſon, at whoſe buriall it was preached, ſuch an example both of liuing, and dying well, as being now by this means made further known, maie through Gods goodnes, provoke many the better to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the ſame: and weighing alſo with my ſelfe, that as his death was precious, in the eies of the Lorde, ſo it was and is, my duety to do anie thing that lyeth in me, to further the continuance of his name, in bleſſed and everlaſting remembrance; I haue yeelded, as your Honours ſee, to this requeſt. Indeede when J preached it, by reaſon of the ſhortnes of time, that then J was tyed vnto; that there might alſo be time, without staying of the aſſembly too long, for the performance of the ſolemne and Honorable funerall rites; J was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to cut off much, that I had thought to have vttered, and but briefly and lightly to run ouer ſundry thinges, which more at large, my purpoſe was then to haue handled. Al which now, I haue thought good according to my firſt full premeditation, in print to ſet downe
<pb facs="tcp:2583:3"/> wherevppon, in remembring what was ſaide, and now in conferring this therewith, ſome difference there will be found: But yet, that will be, not for the ſubſtance or matters therein handled, at all; but onelie that ſome of them are further proſecuted here, and vrged, then for the reaſon aforeſaide, they could be then. And to you three iointlie, I haue beene bolde to dedicate it, becauſe as in nature, ſo in truth, I know the loſſe of this Honorable man, toucheth you three, neereſt: wiſhing and hartely praying you, with the reading and meditation of the matters herein conteyned, to comfort your ſelues, and to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate your ſorrow, otherwiſe, for the loſſe of ſuch an one. For hereby you ſhall (I hope) plainely perceiue, that he was ſuch a one, whome the Lorde of ſpeciall fauour towarde him, hath taken hence; and that therefore howſoeuer, we haue loſt him, God hath found hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and that whatſoeuer wee haue loſt, out of all doubt, he hath found both perfect peace, and ioy in ſoule; and moſt ſound and quiet reſt in bodie. And therefore in his reſpect, you ſhall hereby finde, that they that loued him moſt, haue moſt iuſt cauſe to reioice. Jndeede in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of our ſelues, this ſermon will laie before you, that there is iuſt cauſe of mourning, for all that hee hath left behinde him: yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it will ſhew you, that the ende and vſe hereof ought onelie to be this, to awaken vs ſo out of all ſecuritie in our ſinnes, as that wee maie, by heartie repentaunce, and true turning vnto God in time, turne away the fearefull euils, that otherwiſe the taking awaye ſo faſt of ſuch, threatens vs. J trust therefore, if your honours will voutchſafe to take the paines, ſeriouſly to read and to conſider here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that no ſmall comfort and good, will in theſe reſpectes ariſe, and grow vnto you, thereby. And this, J muſt needes ſaie to your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfort, that the great concourſe of people vnto his buriall, and the crying and weeping of all ſortes there, was ſuch: as in my opinion it was a notable argument, that, as he was doubtleſſe, beloued of God, ſo was he vnfeinedlie honoured and loued of men. Herein alſo appeared an euident token of Gods favour towardes him, that as he had liued honorably, ſo it pleaſed the Lord, to take him hence, according to his owne vſuall, and often repeated requeſt, (though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had beene a great man of warre) in ſuch peace, in his own bedde,
<pb facs="tcp:2583:3"/> in his owne houſe, as he did; and withall to bring him, with ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as queſtionles he was brought to his graue. For when the waies of men haue not pleaſed the Lorde, wee finde often in the ſcriptures, that they both haue beene threatned, and that ſo it hath come to paſſe, that they ſhould not haue the honour of the ordinarie buriall, meete and vſed to perſons of their eſtate: as wee maie read and ſee, <hi>Pſal. 79. verſ. 3.1. King. 21.23. &amp; 2.9.35. &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Ier. 22 18. &amp;c.</hi> And of the contrarie, we finde it very often noted in the ſame, as an argument of Gods favour, towards them when men haue ſo died, as that they attained vnto honorable and convenient buriall. As wee maie finde touching <hi>Abraham Gen. 25.8.</hi> touching <hi>Iacob Gen. 49. &amp; 50. verſ. 29. &amp;c. &amp; 2.3. &amp;c.</hi> touching <hi>Dauid 2. King. 2. verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</hi> yea and touching Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Ioh. 19 ver. 38.39. &amp;c.</hi> Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie therefore in this reſpect, in my iudgment, are you Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ladie his wife, to be commended, eſpeciallie thinges concerning the world, ſtanding with you now, no otherwiſe then your good frends know they do; that you haue thus honorably as you haue, perfourmed this duetie vnto him. For though J am of the ſame opinion, that he was, that wrote that tract, <hi>de cura pro mortuis gerenda,</hi> of care to be taken for the dead, commonlie fathered vpon <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> that <hi>iſta omnia, id eſt curatio funcris, conditio ſepultura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; pompa exequiarum, magis viuorum ſunt ſolatia, quam ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia mortuorum Cap. 2.</hi> that is, that al theſe thinges, the care had about the dead bodie, the maner of the buriall, and the ſolemnitie of the funeral obſequies, are rather comfortes for the liuing, then anie helpes of the dead; yet J am of this iudgement thereof, ſo they bee done and vſed without ſuperstition, and but as is decent and ſit, for the ſtate of the perſon (as in this caſe J am ſure they were) they are commendable tokens and arguments, both of dutifull loue and regarde, in thoſe they leaue behinde, towardes them: and alſo ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie good means, to ſhew and nouriſh their hope, of a ioiful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable reſurrection. Do we not read, euen that our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt himſelfe, defended Marie Magdalens fact, when ſome of hls diſciples murmured at it, in powring a box of very coſtly ointment on his head: in that ſhe did it to bury him. Mat. 26.
<pb facs="tcp:2583:4"/> ve. 7 &amp;c.</hi> And is it not reported, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, both of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Nicodemus, that the one,</hi> to the dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t burial of Chriſt, beſtowed vpon him <hi>a ſepulchre, &amp; linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloths to wrap his body in,</hi> &amp; that the other <hi>brought mirhhe &amp; aloes, an 100. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d weight, that ſo with ſweet odours, according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of the Iews, they might bury him? Ioh, 19.38.39. &amp;c.</hi> Surely <hi>Gen 50.</hi> it is recorded, that when old father <hi>Iacob</hi> was dead, &amp; the care of his funeral was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto his ſon <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that not onlie <hi>he cauſed by his phiſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, his body to be embalmed, but alſo with an Honorable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany &amp; great ſolemnity, though to his very great coſt, according to his fathers deſire, he carried it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegipt into the land of Canaan, to bury him with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Iſaac, in the caue &amp; field that Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had bought to bury in, of Ephron the Hittite:</hi> &amp; this is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, &amp; was indeed, both a notable argument in him of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards his dead father, &amp; alſo of hope that he had of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And therfore, though I wiſh, that al ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; needles &amp; vndecent ſuperfluitie be aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doned in ſuch caſes, &amp; generally in the burial of the dead; yet I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but greatly like &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend, that ſuch, decent &amp; comlie order be kept therin; that maie according to euery mans degree, argue &amp; nouriſh both theſe amongſt al his welwillers, that he hath left behinde him. And therefore once againe, I cannot but reioice, in al your behalfes, that you were alſo of one minde, as I know you were, that this laſt duety ſhould ſo Honorably be performed vnto the bodie of this Honorable Lord as it was, &amp; ther in you maie all take comfort. Further, it ought to be now, ground of no ſmal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation vnto you al three, that one, hath had of him, that thus Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norablie liued an died, ſuch a ſon in Law; the other ſuch a huſband; &amp; the third ſo worthie a father, as he was. For if it be matter of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort of the contrarie as everie one ſeeth by experience, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wil confeſſe it is; whie ſhould not this alwaies be matter of reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to euerie of your Honors, as oft as either you remember him, or heare him remembred by others? And ſuch a neere and domeſticall example ought both to comfort much, &amp; alſo to provoke to imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame: &amp; I hope &amp; pray God that it maie: that ſo yet, though
<pb facs="tcp:2583:4"/> to vs he be dead &amp; gone, yet his vertues &amp; noble qualities, maie ſtil liue &amp; ſhine, to the comfort of al his welwillers, in his, that he hath left behinde him. Finallie iuſtlie maie it be a comfort vnto you, &amp; ſo to the praiſe &amp; glorie of God, I would wiſh you al hartelie to take it ſo and vſe it, that euerie one of you (to ſaie no more) haue ſo iuſt cauſe, both before God &amp; man to comfort your ſelues one in another as you haue: one that ſhe hath ſuch a daughter, &amp; daughters ſonne; the other, that the Lord in his mercifull providence, hath giuen her both ſuch an Honorable careful &amp; louing mother, and a good and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſon; &amp; the third, that he hath ſo vertuous, religious &amp; Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, both grandmother &amp; mother. O howe ought this to abate and moderate your former ſorrow, ſeeing now there is no remedie? And what an excellent and ſtrong means are you, and J hope will be, as long as you liue together, not onlie of comfort everie waie one vnto another, but of counſailing, directing, and ſtrengthening, where moſt neede is, one of another, in a holie courſe? A threefold corde is not eaſilie broken, ſaith the Preacher, <hi>Cap. 4. ver. 12.</hi> But the greateſt comfort of all, that both you and all other of Gods children in the midſt of all the afflictions of this life, haue, is this; that that God whom you ſerue, <hi>remaineth for euer one &amp; ſelfe ſame, that hee is al ſufficient &amp; an exceeding great rewarde to his,</hi> that his providence howſoeuer thinges fall out ſtandeth immutable, and that therfore without al queſtion, howſoeuer we cannot perceiue it as the firſt, <hi>al things,</hi> &amp; therefore euen thoſe thinges alſo, which ſeeme vnto vs moſt to croſſe the ſame, <hi>ſhal by his diuine wiſedome and power, turne to the good, and benefit of his. Rom. 8.28.</hi> With al theſe things therfore, once againe, beſeeching you to comfort your ſelues, &amp; one another: praying the Lord effectuallie you maie ſo doe, &amp; that all his good bleſſings to your own euerlaſting ſaluation maie be powred and continued vpon everie of you, &amp; all yours for euer, J ceaſe from anie further troubling of your Honors, at this time. As Blechley this firſt of <hi>December. 1593.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors alwaies moſt ready and willing</hi> to be as commandement. Thomas Sparke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2583:5"/>
            <head>IN OBITVM CLARISSIMI HE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rois, Domini Arthuri Greij. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Curuae in terras animae, quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> piorum</l>
               <l>Creditis extinctas vnà cum corpore mentes.</l>
               <l>O vanos queſtus; ô pectora plena furoris,</l>
               <l>St quando in ſuperûm ſedes quos <hi>Ioua</hi> recepit,</l>
               <l>Speratis fletu rurſus deducere Coelo.</l>
               <l>Debetis fateor lachrymas &amp; Iuſta ſepultis;</l>
               <l>Sed tranſire modum, ſcelus; &amp; perijſſe putare</l>
               <l>Quos <hi>Chriſtus</hi> ſeruat, mortem qui morte peremit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At dolor extorquet luctus in funera tanti</l>
               <l>Herois. Certè noſtrae non infima gentis</l>
               <l>Gloria defluxit, grauis inclementia fati</l>
               <l>Cum tulit hunc terris, vt lucida viſeret aſtra.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is fuit ex atauis Heroibus editus Heros,</l>
               <l>Relligione pius, conſtantimente probatus,</l>
               <l>Conſilio prudens, iuſtis animoſus in armis.</l>
               <l>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llatis ſignis rigidos qui fudit Hybernos,</l>
               <l>Quos per inacceſſos ſaltus, vdaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> paludes</l>
               <l>Inſequitur, ſubigens extremo Marte rebelles.</l>
               <l>Pro patriâ pugnans, ſanctis ariſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fociſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</l>
               <l>(Turma Caledonias dum vaſtat Gallica terras)</l>
               <l>Ore cicatrices, aduerſo pectore fortis</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulnera multa tulit, nunquam dare terga coactus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Talis apud Graecos magnus celebratur <hi>Achilles.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Talis &amp; <hi>Albertus</hi> cui magni nomen <hi>Achillei</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Teutonis or a dedit, ſurgunt vbi moenia <hi>Brenni.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hoc animo <hi>Decij,</hi> hoc olim caluere <hi>Metelli,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Qui ſe pro patriâ, pro libertate Penatum</l>
               <l>Deuouere neci, quos laus aeterna moratur.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ioannes Sanfordus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2583:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah. 57. verſe. 1.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1</hi>
                     </bibl> The righteous periſheth, &amp; no man conſidereth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hart: and mercifull men are taken away, and no man vnderſtandeth that the righteous is taken away, from the evell to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2</hi>
                     </bibl> Peace ſhall come: they ſhall reſt in their beddes, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that walketh before him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE occaſion of this our preſent meeting (Right honorable, Right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and wel be loued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord and Sauiour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and the conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aies and cili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in we liue, haue for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> me, to make cheefe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> portion of ſcripture, at this time. For nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the Lord hath now taken from vs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe, this Right Noble, and worthy Lord, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall we are here now about, and the buriall of whoſe bodie wee are anone to fee, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>wiſe hee hath, within theſe few yeares, taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by death from this land, very many of our moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Earles, Lords and Knights, as it is wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> beſide many others of all other ſorts and eſtates of the beſt diſpoſition, &amp; that the greateſt part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that are left behinde, are growne is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> height in all ſin and impiety: yet vniuerſally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2583:6"/> where amongſt vs, there is ſuch a groſſe and ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſecurity to be ſeene, that doubtles, as iuſtly maie we now, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in his time, in the bitternes of our ſoules, cry out and ſay, <hi>the righteous periſheth, and no man conſidereth it in heart, and mercifull men are taken away, and no man vnderſtandeth that the righteous is taken away from the euell to come.</hi> Onely this with him, in this caſe, we haue to comfort our ſelues withall, that howſoeuer the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly iudge of the deathes of ſuch; that in very deede, the Lord thereby in his great loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour hath taken them away, before the euel come, which he hath prepared for them, that hereby will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot in time, be drawne to repentance. And that, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer whiles ſuch liued in this vnkinde and wicked world, they could neuer enioy either ſound peace in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, or quiet reſt in their bodies, for vering and gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing themſelues, at the vngodlines of others rounde about them; yet euery one that walketh before God in righteouſnes, and mercy, and ſo is taken away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thus walking, is ſure immediatly vppon his death, to enter poſſeſſion in ſoule of an euerlaſting &amp; moſt comfortable <hi>peace,</hi> and in bodye to reſt moſt ſoundly and quietly <hi>in the bed</hi> that the Lorde hath made therefore, vntill at the laſt day, it riſe againe, and for euer to be ioyned with the ſoule in moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and conſummate ioy in the kingdome of heauen. Wherfore ſeeing theſe words of the prophet, and the matter therein contayned, thus fit our preſent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2583:6"/> I beſeech you giue me leaue to doe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that I can to lead you ſo into the due meditation therof, that we all may make that holy and good vſe therof that we ſhould, both to reforme that in time which is amiſſe in any of vs, and to comfort and ſtrengthen vs in that which is well begunne.</p>
            <p>His wordes, in my iudgement, containe &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint or expoſtulation; and a comfort or conſolation. The complaint is againſt the vngodly aliue, in the behalfe of the godly departed: &amp; the com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, for the godly, againſt the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d opinions of the vngodly of them. The matter in general that he comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of, is, the wonderfull careleſneſſe and ſecurity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaw in the people of his time; which in particular he notes they ſhewed firſt, in not taking to heard as they ſhould, the deathes of moſt worthy men, and then in not once vnderſtanding that the Lordes end there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was, not only to ſhew them great favour in taking them away from the euell to come, but alſo thereby to threaten ſome great euill, to be comming on apace vpon the impenitent &amp; ſecure, that they leſſe behinde them. And let his words be well markt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſhal finde in the deliuering of this comfort, he doth firſt deſcribe them, whom he would comfort, &amp; then ſets downe the comforts that belong to ſuch and theſe he deſcribeth in generall, in the latter ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, to be eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that walketh before God; and in particuler, in the other to be righteous and mercifull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the comfortes that herein hee layes downe for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2583:7"/> ſuch, ere either ſuch as concerne them dying, or dead, and of each kind he giues two: the firſt are theſe, that the Lords end in taking them away by death, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the vngodly think to the contrary, is in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to take them away before the euill come, that he haſteneth to bring vppon others: and that their death is no periſhing vnto them, though the prophane and wicked ſo think, but in truth a gathering of them vp from amongſt the vngodly, with whome whiles they liued, to their griefe &amp; trouble they were mingled; to ioyne them to the bleſſed &amp; holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the Saints in heauen &amp; the other two, that immediatly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death they enter into fruition of, are theſe, that thereupon ſtreight in ſoule they enter into peace, and in their bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they reſt in their beds, that is in their graues, or places whatſoeuer, the Lorde in his prouidence hath allotted them. This order therefore &amp; methode, let vs nowe follow in further handling &amp; examining theſe wordes of the Prophet.</p>
            <p>But that the better we may attaine and finde out his full ſcope and drift herein, we are firſt to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that theſe words of his, haue their neceſſary co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, and connexion, with the foure laſt verſes of the former Chapter: which the better to leade the reader to ſee and perceaue, <hi>Tremelius</hi> in his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Bible, hath begunne this <hi>57.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where thoſe foure verſes beginne. Marke therefore, I beſeech you, that in the firſt of thoſe foure verſes that I ſpeake of, the Prophet calles
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2583:7"/> 
               <hi>for the beaſtes of the fielde and forreſt to come to eate, and deuour,</hi> by which woordes, by a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue kinde of ſpeech, he denounceth againſt that people ſome fearefull deſtruction, that ſhould come vppon them and great ſlaughter that ſhould he made of them. Therein doubtleſſe hauing an eie to that, which ſhould come to paſſe, when Nabuchadnezer the king of Babell, ſhoulde inuade their country, and deſtroy Hieruſalem, temple &amp; all; ſlaying whom he liſt, and leading the reſt into captiuity. For <hi>Hieremie,</hi> another prophet, whome the Lorde rayſed vppe vnto that people after <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time, reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that iudgement, telles them in his ninth Chapter verſe <hi>22.</hi> that when that ſhould be, <hi>their Carkaſſes ſhould he as doung vpon the earth and be ſcattered as handfuls after the mower<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where there is none to gather them vp,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againe in his <hi>34</hi> Chapter, hauing plainly &amp; expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this iudgement againſt them, in like phraſe to this, verſe <hi>20.</hi> he ſhewes them, that when it ſhoulde be executed vpon them, <hi>their dead bodies ſhould be meat for the foules of heauen, &amp; the beaſts of the field.</hi> But that by thus calling the beaſts together, as it were to a ſolemn ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quet, it is the vſe and faſhion of the ſpirit of God in the ſcriptures, to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome horrible and dreadfull deſtruction, wee maie moſt clearely ſee, <hi>Ezech <hi>39.</hi> verſ. <hi>18.19.</hi>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>20.</hi> &amp; <hi>Reuel. <hi>19.</hi> verſ. <hi>17.</hi>
               </hi> Where it is euident that to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſuch a matter, both <hi>the foules of the aire
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2583:8"/> and beaſtes of the field are ſolemnly cald for,</hi> as it were, <hi>to feede at the Lordes table to their full, of the fleſh and blood of kings, princes, nobles, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; of others of al ſortes.</hi> Wherfore it is moſt certaine, that our Prophet here, by the like phraſe, gaue this people of the kingdome of <hi>Iudah</hi> to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that ſuch a iudgement as I haue ſaide, was prepared for them, and haſtening faſt towards them.</p>
            <p>Now hauing done this thus, in the firſt of the <hi>4.</hi> verſes immediatly going before my text; in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three, he layes downe, that one ſpeciall prognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tication, and haſtening cauſe thereof was this, that they that in reſpect of their places and maintenance therefore, ought to haue beene as their watchmen to tell them of their ſinnes, and to forewarne them of the iudgementes of God therefore to come vppon them, were ſuch, as either for lacke of ſkill or will, in that reſpect were no better then dumbe dogs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in ſleeping, and that yet they were ſo cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and ambitious, that they coulde neuer be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied withall, giuing themſelues moſt ſecurely to all delicacy and volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuouſnes of liuing. Whereby by the way, we may ſee, that when in any kingdome it may iuſtly and truely be thus ſaide of ſuch; that then euen thereby, that people haue a moſt certaine cauſe giuen them to feare, ſome grievous iudgement not to be far off. For how can it be, but when it is thus with theſe kinde of men, it muſt bee as bad, if not worſe, with them whom theſe, both for life and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2583:8"/> ſhoulde go before and guide? For if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> darkenes, what elſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we looked for in the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? And if the ſunne haue giuen ouer ſhining, and be as it were quite ſet vppon the toppe of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, what ſhew can it make in the valleyes? God of his mercy therfore gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we may, be every day more and more vnlike the kingdome of <hi>Iudah</hi> in this point. Well, the Prophet hauing thus drawen one argument from the corrupt eſtate of the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in his time, that ſuch a heavy iudgement, (as I haue ſhewed he denounced) was comming apace on, againſt the people of the kingdome of <hi>Iudah:</hi> hauing a deſire fully to perſwade them that it was ſo, the better to awaken them and to draw them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, if it were poſſible, to preuent the ſame: in theſe wordes of my text, he giues them another moſt ſure and certaine ſigne and token thereof. And it is this, that in ſo bad times, as thoſe were, wherin ſinne had ſo ouerflowed al eſtates, the Lordes taking away by death, ſo many of their beſt and godlieſt men (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the number was before but ſmall) was a plaine demonſtration, that ſuch an euel was ſhortly to come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe whom they left behind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the rather, becauſe notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding this was a heauy iudgment of it ſelfe, thus to haue their moſt worthy men taken away, and clerely ſhewed that yet there was a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier comming: (the people continued and went on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in ther olde lewd courſe, in all ſecurity, neither fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the preſent blow, that hereby the Lorde g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2583:9"/> them, nor yet thereby taking any occaſion to thinke, that a further was threatned. Other argumentes he could haue vſed to this purpoſe, but with theſe two, as though theſe two, were inſteede of all the reſt, and were of themſelues moſt ſufficent, to perſwade this matter, he contents himſelfe. Wherefore looking now into the daies and times wherein we liue, if it be ſo, that we cannot deny, but that the manners of men, and the falling out of things amongſt vs, geue ground for theſe two arguments to be vrged and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt vs, we may and ought to learne hereby, vnleſſe we be diſpoſed to ſhowe our ſelues to be a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that nothing can feare or drawe from ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to true repentance; that it ſtandes vs vppon ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, euen hereby to take warning to looke better to our ſelues and to our waies, then hitherto wee haue done. As for the former of theſe argumentes, whether there haue not bin and yet are, two many ſuch in the place of watchmen amongſt vs, as the Prophet hath deſcribed, to grounde that vppon: I referre to your owne iudgement, who perhaps knowe it better then my ſelfe: but touching the other, laide downe here in my text, I dare boldly affirme, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had neuer iuſter cauſe to vrge that in his time, then we haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nowe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore now vnderſtanding as we doe, vppon what occaſion and to what ende theſe wordes were vttered by him, let vs according to the order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode before therein obſerued, go on in the further
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2583:9"/> weighing &amp; conſidering thereof. The righteous man periſheth (ſaith he) ſpeaking in the ſinguler number for the plurall, as it is euident in the next Clauſe, where ſpeaking ſtill of the ſame, he termes them in the plurall number mercifull men. Whereby it is cleare, that this was ſpoken by hint in reſpect of ſuch a time, of his propheſying, wherein many ſuch as here he ſpeaks of, by one kinde of death or other were taken hence. But whereas, by the firſt verſe of this booke of his propheſies, it appeares, that he prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyed <hi>in the daies of Vzziah, Iothan, Ahaz,</hi> and <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> kinges of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and ſome of the ancient Rabbins, and other Chriſtian ancient fathers, haue thought, that he himſelfe was ſawn to death in the firſt yeare of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> (the conſideration whereof, hath made many, to vnderſtand that <hi>Hebr. <hi>11.</hi> verſe <hi>37.</hi>
               </hi> where the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the deaths of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of the godly, in the time of the olde teſtament, ſaith, <hi>ſome were hewn a ſunder,</hi> or as ſome rather tranſlate it, <hi>ſawn a ſunder,</hi> as ſpoken properly of the death of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> vnder this idolatrous tyrant) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the interpreters of this place, they al are not of one minde, touching the time, in reſpect wherof, theſe wordes were ſet downe. For ſome refer them, to ſome time of the <hi>16.</hi> yeares, that <hi>Ahaz</hi> reigned, ſome to the firſt yeare of the raigne of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> &amp; others thinke, they were ſpoken in regard of ſome time of the reigne of <hi>Ezechiah.</hi> They that refer them to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haz,</hi> or <hi>Manaſſes</hi> times think, that the Prophet here
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2583:10"/> ſpeaketh, not onely of ſuch righteous and mercifull men, as in thoſe times died ordinary deaths by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes vpon their beds, but eſpecially of ſuch, as were put to death by thoſe idolatrous and wicked Kings. And indeede, likely inough it is, that in their times, many ſuch for miſliking their proceedings, and not conforming themſelues thereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, came to their ends. For <hi>Ahaz,</hi> was ſo groſſe an idolater, <hi>that he burnt incenſe in the valley of Benhinnom, and burnt his ſonnes with fire</hi> (or made them paſſe through the fire) <hi>after the abomination of the heathen, 2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 25. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</hi> and he had <hi>Vriah</hi> the prieſt one ready <hi>to follow his idolatrous &amp; wicked commandements in any thing 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</hi> &amp; <hi>16.</hi> and of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the holy ſtory, <hi>2. <hi>Kings</hi> 21. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</hi> &amp;c. &amp; <hi>2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 33. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</hi> &amp;c reports as much ill, as may be: and <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus,</hi> for his part, in the <hi>10.</hi> booke of the antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Iews, chapter the <hi>4.</hi> writes moſt plainly, <hi>that he kild all that he could come by both of the prophets and people that were godly.</hi> And they that refer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Ezechias</hi> time, either refer them to the time, when <hi>he was ſicke vnto death and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered,</hi> as we reade <hi>Iſaiah 35.</hi> or to the time <hi>when he died indeede 2.</hi> Kinges the <hi>20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21.</hi> For the ſicknes that he was ſo ſicke of, and yet recouered, is thought of ſundry learned men, to haue bin the very plague, wherof about that time, many ſuch as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> here ſpeaketh of, by all likelihood died, though he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped; &amp; when he died ſuch a one, doubtles, as he here
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2583:10"/> talkes of, was taken away, and about that time, it may be, many others of the beſt ſort, died alſo. But foraſmuch, as howſoeuer the righteous are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, whether it be by the violent perſecution of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, by the plague, or by any diſeaſe, or means els; yet the prophet might ſpeake of them, whatſoeuer he hath done here: it is very harde for any man, preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to determine, in reſpect of what time of his life, he vttered theſe wordes. Wherefore in that point, to leaue euery man free to his owne iudgement, by his owne wordes ſo much is apparant, that they were ſet downe by him, in reſpect of ſuch a time, when of that ſmall number that were ſuch, as here he deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes, in his opinion, ſo many dropt away, by one kinde of death, or other, that (the ſecurity and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes of the reſt that notwithſtanding conſidered) he had iuſt cauſe to complaine, that no man would lay the deaths of ſuch to heart, or once vnderſtand, that the Lord thereby prognoſticated a further euell to come. And vttering this his complaint, it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy to be noted, that he ſpeaking in the ſenſe of the wicked, careles, and ſecure people in his time, he ſaith, <hi>the righteous periſheth:</hi> thereby giuing vs to vnderſtand, that indeede, that was the faſhion of ſuch, ſo to iudge of thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ether they by their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny had diſpatcht, or who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, otherwiſe by ſome painefull maner of death (whereunto the righteous, is as well ſubiect as others) had taken hence. And indeede wiſedome the <hi>3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-3.</hi> it is ſaid, that in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2583:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſight of the vnwiſe, <hi>the righteous (whoſe ſoules are in the hand of God and not torment ſhal touch them <hi>ver.</hi> 1.) appeare to die, &amp; their end is thought grieuous, and their departing from vs to be deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and againe, <hi>Chapt. <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </hi> they are brought in confeſſing aſmuch themſelues, <hi>(ſaying we fooles, thought their life madnes, and their end to haue beene without honor.</hi> And this doubtles, was ſome occaſion of griefe to the holy Prophet, and ſo, ſome cauſe of this his complaint, that he ſawe the wicked ſo ready, thus lewdly to iudge &amp; ſpeake of the deaths of ſuch. And therefore to reforme them in this point, and to make it appeare, what he would haue al men to thinke of the deathes of ſuch, what maner of death ſoeuer it were, he, by and by, addeth that ſuch are <hi>but taken away, or conueyed, or gathered hence,</hi> (for ſo the word is alſo tranſlated of ſome) <hi>from the euill to come.</hi> Further in that he ſaith, <hi>no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidereth it in hart, that the righteous periſheth: &amp; none vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, that the righteous &amp; merciful men are taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euil to come,</hi> it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the Prophet was of this iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that it was a thing to be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, ſorrowed for, &amp; hartily to be complained of, if in ſuch bad times as theſe were, wherof he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, men ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in ſecurity, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the Lord ſeeketh by taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt worthy away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, to driue them from the ſame; yea that it was a ſtrong argument, or ſigne, of ſome great euill, likely ſhortly to fall vpon them that would not thereby be awaken. Seing therfore that euen this yeare, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2583:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> but reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, that the Lord hath taken hence, firſt the Lord Wentworth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Earle of Darby, and nowe as we ſee this noble and worthy Lord Gray, al in their ſeueral places and countries, right excellent men, and beſides, we cannot be ignorant, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe <hi>8.</hi> or <hi>9.</hi> yeares likewiſe, the Lord hath taken from vs, a great number of the moſt worthie &amp; noble Earles. Lords, and Knights, that England hath had many a day; and that alſo by wars, the plagne, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes, we haue loſt within a very ſmall time, more then we can number of very valiant, wiſe, and vertuous men; who ſeeth not, that in this reſpect we may ſay, aſwell as euer <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did, <hi>the righteous &amp; mercifull men are taken away?</hi> And as for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the reſt, for all this, ſurely I feare me, we are no whit behinde the people in his time, &amp; the reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, in as great da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger as they were, God of his mercy giue vs grace to ſee our fault therein, &amp; to amend in time.</p>
            <p>Thus we hauing ſeene in generall, what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plained of, and what driue him ſo to doe; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we are to make therof, is to be as careful a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that we geue none ſuch as he was, any ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to morne and complain of vs, as he did of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> people of his time. And the better that we may, as we ought indeede, make this vſe of his complaint, let vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſee in particular, how he proues them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as of whome in generall, he had occaſion thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine. The firſt reaſon is, <hi>that none conſidered in heart,</hi> or as it is in the Hebrewe, <hi>no man</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hart that the righteous ſo periſhed</hi> and were taken
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2583:12"/> away as we haue heard. The vſe of which phraſe in the ſcripture is, to expreſſe a carefull and harty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of a thing, and in this place doubtles ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the prophet meaneth, that no man ſo ſorrowed in his heart for the dropping away ſo faſt of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and mercifull men, as there was cauſe, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the loſſe of ſuch. Otherwiſe in another ſence, there were enow then wee may bee ſure, that laide the deathes of ſuch but too faſt to their hearts: to harten and harden on themſelues in ſin and impiety; for that by this meanes, they that moſt bridled and curbed them, from bold and ſecure ruſhing and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out, beyond all bondes of piety and honeſty, to wring and wrong others, or to defile themſelues, were taken out of their way. And this the prophet himſelfe, both in the verſe immediatly going before my text, and in the next verſe but one after it, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheweth he did perceiue; for in the former of theſe two verſes, (in that I meane next before my text) he bringes in the wicked liuing in thoſe very times, when, the righteous died thus faſt, hartening themſelues in this manner, ſaying, <hi>Come I will bring wine, and we will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drinke, and to morrow ſhall bee as this day and much more abundant,</hi> and in the other, after that, in the very next verſe after my text, hee hath giuen ſuch their due tyles, <hi>calling them witches children and ſonnes of the adulterer and whore, he faieth,</hi> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>on whom haue ye ieſted, on whom haue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2583:12"/> you gaped and thruſt out your toung?</hi> thereby as it ſhould ſeeme, deſcribing the triumphing and inſul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of the wicked, that the righteous and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men, that troubled &amp; croſſed them in their waies were now as they thought, as water ſpilt vppon the ground. And ſurely, it is much to be feared, that euen now amongſt vs, there are in corners, and when they are where they may be bold, that in this prophane &amp; wicked manner, lay to their hartes, to ſolace &amp; there them withall, the deathes of the moſt worthie men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. But whoſoeuer they bee, that thus take occaſion, to make themſelues merry from hence, from whence they ſhoulde indeede take occaſion to mourne and lament, let them vnderſtand, that the Lord by this our prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> hauing <hi>called that people to faſting and mourning that were in his time, and they falling to feaſting and laughing, he tels them that that their ſin, was declared in the eares of the Lord of hoſts, and that therevpon, this was his flat decree and ſentence of them, that that their iniquitie ſhoulde not bee purged vntill they died. <hi>Cap.</hi> 22. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</hi> Wherefore the better to make vs to take to hart, the dying of the worthy men amongſt vs, not in this wrong fence, but in the ſence and manner that here it appeares the Prophet wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: let vs now conſider what reaſon hee had to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, and to take this for one ſpeciall particuler ſigne of intollerable ſecurity, that men woulde not mourne and lament, and ſo laie to their heartes, the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2583:13"/> deathes of ſuch doubtles, he knew, that ſuch kinde of men, were the bands &amp; ſinnews, yea the very pillors, and buttreſſes, of the good eſtate, both of the Church, &amp; common weale; and that therfore the taking away of ſuch (howſoeuer ſecure &amp; prophane men made no reckoning thereof) was indeed a heauy iudgment of God vpon al that they left behind them. For the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, are therby the more hardned, and hartened to al iniquitie, ſo to haſten Gods further iudgements vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the land wherin ſuch liue, &amp; the Godly are therby greatly weakned, in this wicked world before men, for lacke of aſſiſtaunce by ſuch againſt the wrongs &amp; oppreſſions of the vngodly. And it is euident that he knew, this moſt perfectly, for in his third Chapter he hauing threatned the people of his time, that for their ſins the Lord woulde take from them <hi>the ſtay and ſtrength,</hi> though in the particulariſing wherein the ſtay and ſtrength of a citty and country lyeth, hee name <hi>bread and drinke in the</hi> firſt place, becauſe (as it ſhould ſeeme) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men cannot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue at all, yet by &amp; by he reckoneth, <hi>the ſtrong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the man of warre, the iudge, the Prophet, the prudent, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the Honorable, the counceller &amp;c.</hi> As them, without whom neither Citty nor countrey, can long enioy anie good beeing. For ſuch being taken a waie, be ſhewes, the conſequent thereof is likely to be this, that ſome as vnfit <hi>as children and babes to rule,</hi> ſhal ſucceede them, whereuppon would follow great <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion one of another, and confuſion.</hi> And it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2583:13"/> by the conference of theſe <hi>2.</hi> places together, as he threatned that people for their ſins this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, about the beginning of his propheſying, ſo or he died, he ſawe the ſame in great meaſure, in exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon them. Howe could he therefore, but in this reſpect mourne, in that all this not withſtanding, he could obſerue none, that mourned vnder the burden of this iudgement, as they ſhould. For as it argues, a wonderfull harde heart, either in childe or ſeruant, that will not once melt or mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, when the he a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie blowes of father or maiſter are ſounding vpon their ſhoulders, ſo cannot this be taken but as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both then &amp; no we, of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollerable ſenſeleſnes, if in the daily execution of this heauie iudgement of God vpon vs, we ſhould ſhew our ſelues, by our not taking or to heart at all, to be ſuch as neither ſee it, nor feele it to be a iudgement, or any puniſhment vpon vs. Yea the very wicked themſelues (howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in their own fooliſh &amp; vaine conceits, they haue cauſe to be merry, for the death of ſuch) yee indeede and truth, if they looke well into gods dealing with his own deare ſeruants, in taking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, through many tribulations, &amp; often in the end alſo, by painful and tormenting kinde of deathes, haue iuſt cauſe, thereby miniſtred vnto them, to ſay and thinke with <hi>Peter <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18. if iudgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the houſe of God, and the righteous them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo hardly be ſaued, what ſhall the end be of them that obey not the goſpell of God, &amp; where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2583:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2583:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2583:15"/> ſhall the vngodly and ſinner appeare? For if theſe things be don to a green tree, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.31. what ſhall be done to the drie?</hi> But and if this will not ſerue, to make ſuch to bethink them of their owne ſinnes, and of the iudgements of God due vnto them for the ſame, I would wiſh them further to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that when the enemies of gods people, were ſo far off from taking out this leſſon, by beholding the miſeries and afflictions of gods own people, that rather they tooke occaſion, becauſe of their owne flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing eſtate in health and wealth for that preſent, to inſult and to triumph ouer them; that the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> was commanded by the Lord, to ſay vnto al ſuch, <hi>drink al &amp; be drunken, ſpew and fal, &amp; riſe no more, becauſe of the ſword that I will ſend amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you, but and if they refuſe to take the cup at thy hand to drinke, ſaith the Lord vnto him, then tell them thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, ye ſhal certainly drink, for loe I begin to plague the citty where my name is cald vpon, and ſhall you go free? you ſhall not go quite. <hi>Ierem. <hi>25.</hi> verſ. 27.</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> a while made themſelues merry, at the death of <hi>Naboth 1.</hi> Kings <hi>21,</hi> but marke the ſequele of that ſtory, and you ſhal finde, that neither of them had any cauſe to be merry, nor any of their poſterity, ere the Lord had done with them for it. Wherefore <hi>though the vngoldy for a time, liue, wax old, and grow in wealth, and their ſeed be eſtabliſhed in their ſight with them, and their generation before their eies,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2583:15"/> &amp; their houſes be peaceable &amp; without feare and the rod of God be not vpon them,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> obſerued it was with ſome of them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was far otherwiſe with him, <hi>Cap. <hi>21.</hi> verſ. <hi>7.</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c. or though they find it to be with them as <hi>Dauid</hi> noted, when it was nothing ſo well with himſelfe, <hi>Pſal. <hi>73.</hi> verſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>that there be no bands in their death, but they are luſly and ſtrong, that they be not in trouble as other men, nor be plagued with others, &amp; that therfore pride is as a chein vnto them, &amp; cruelty couereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a garment, and their eies ſtand out for fatnes, and they haue more then their heart can wiſh &amp;c.</hi> Yet neither let this diſmay the godly, nor be taken to bee any ſound ground of confort for the other. Indeede it appeares, that euen the very godly haue ſometimes beene offended &amp; troubled hereat, inſomuch that <hi>Iob</hi> himſelfe <hi>Cap. <hi>21.</hi> verſ. <hi>6.</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Dauid Pſal. 73. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</hi> and <hi>3.</hi> Yea euen <hi>Ieremie <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</hi> and <hi>3.</hi> and <hi>Habacuk</hi> an other Prophet of the Lord, <hi>Cap. <hi>1.</hi> verſ <hi>13.</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>14.</hi> doe moſt plainly confeſſe aſmuch, by themſelues. Notwithſtanding certaine it is, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uids</hi> rule is very ſound &amp; good in this caſe, and of all the godly to be followed, which is, <hi>that they ſhould not fret themſelues becauſe of the wicked, nor for him that proſpereth in his way, and bringeth his enterpriſes to paſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi> For let both the godly, the better to preſerue them from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit diſcouraged herewith, &amp; the other, the eaſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſtay them, from triumphing hereby vnderſtand,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2583:16"/> that though indeede it be found true by experience, through the corrupt and blind nature of men, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſentence againſt and euell woorke is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted ſpeedily, that therefore the hartes of the children of men in them, are ſet vpon euel, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ</hi> 11.</hi> inſomuch, that the vngodly, finding that God lets them ſome times alone: therefore, as God complaines <hi>Pſa. <hi>50.</hi> verſ. <hi>21.</hi>
               </hi> are even ready <hi>to think, that he is like them,</hi> that yet all ſuch ſhall moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely finde in the end, that if they thus <hi>deſpiſe the long ſuffering of God, which ſhoulde prouoke them to repentance, that they doe but heape vp vengeance againſt the day of vengeance. <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.</hi> For it followeth in the ſame place of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes laſt cited, immediatly: <hi>though a ſinner do evil an hundred times and God prolongeth his daies, that yet he knew, that it ſhould be well with them that feare the Lord, and do reuerence before him but it ſhall not be well to the wicked, neither ſhal he prolong his daies: he ſhall be like a ſhadow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he feareth not before God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.</hi> And likewiſe in the <hi>50</hi> Pſalme, to anſwere that wicked and blaſphemous thought of the vngodlie, it preſently followeth, as ſpoken by God himſelfe, <hi>but I will reproue thee, and ſet thy ſinnes in order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee:</hi> whereuppon moſt not ably and vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Lord alſo further breaketh out into this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <hi>Oh conſider this yee that forget God, leaſt I teare you in pieces, and there be none that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2583:16"/> can deliuer you.</hi> Yea euen <hi>Iob</hi> himſelfe after that a while he had troubled himſelfe, with muſing vppon the proſperity of the wicked, he could ſay, <hi>that in the ende, the Lorde woulde deuide their liues in his wrath, and that they ſhoulde be as ſtubble before the winde, and as chaffe that the ſtorme carieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and that God would lay vp the ſorrow of the father for his children, &amp; when he rewardeth him, he ſhould ſee it. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo; how much ſoeuer he was troubled before, at, and with, the proſperity of the wicked, <hi>yet when once hee went into the ſanctuarie of God, then he confeſſeth he vnderſtoode their ende, &amp; that God had ſet them in ſlippery places, and did caſt them downe into deſolation, and that they were ſoddenly deſtroied, periſhed, &amp; horrily conſumed <hi>Pſa.</hi> 73. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> And the like might be noted of <hi>Ieremie</hi> and <hi>Habacuk,</hi> who notwithſtanding their reaſoning with god about his ſuffring the wicked to proſper, in the places before quoted, yet through that cloud &amp; miſt, plainly ſhew, in the verie ſame places that they ſaw &amp; knew, <hi>hee was righteous, had pure eyes &amp; could not ſee and behold wickednes,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giuing ſuch to vnderſtand, that howſoeuer it wee w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a time, that yet in the end, the Lord would pay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home. Notably therfore is it to this end, that is written in the <hi>5</hi> Chapter of the book of Wiſedom, where the wicked are brought in, bewailing their folly, for iudging ſo badly, as they had, of the liues &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2583:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> deathes of the righteous, and bewayling the vanity and impiety of their own, when they had once found all their pompe and pleaſure to bee, <hi>but as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, a poſt, or as the flying of a bird, or arrowe in the aire, or ſayling of a ſhip in the ſea, which ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly are paſt and gon, &amp; leaue no tract behinde them,</hi> &amp; when they had learned by experience <hi>that al the hope of ſuch,</hi> (which is moſt fearful) <hi>is but as duſt, fome, &amp; ſmoke,</hi> which moſt eaſely is ſcattered &amp; carried away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the winde &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt. Cauſe therfore without al queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very wicked, in the ſeeing the Lord take away, &amp; deal w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the beſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he doth, to tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble &amp; quake before him, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their own ſins, &amp; ſo to take to hart, their deaths: &amp; ſo was this a ſufficient cauſe, to mooue <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to complaine, and to take it as an argument, of moſt dangerous ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, that he could finde none of them, that woulde thus doe. So therfore we are to account it, if all this not withſtanding, we finde it in this reſpect no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amongſt vs, a certaine ſigne of the like, &amp; therfore to threatten vs, as it did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome further iudgment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular proofe of the ſecurity, that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaines of in the people of his time, comes now to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered of, which he expreſſeth, ſaying, <hi>merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men are taken away, &amp; no man vnderſtandeth that the righteous is taken away, from the euell to come:</hi> word for word in the original it is thus, <hi>from the faces of euell,</hi> but the ſenſe doubtleſſe is, as our interpreter hath rendred it, and very well will the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2583:17"/> Hebrew phraſe, &amp; the vſe therfore in other places of the ſcripture bear it. And certainly, by this euil, that he ſpeaks of, he vnderſtands y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very euill, that ſhoulde come vpon this kingdome, by the inuaſion of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonian. And yet I am not ignorant that ſome tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt the wicked, &amp; therfore according to that tranſlation, <hi>Enoch</hi> is alleadged as an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe, as we read of <hi>his taking he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by God, when he was but 365 years old,</hi> wheras ſome liued then, aboue <hi>900, <hi>Ge.</hi> 5. <hi>ve.</hi> 24.</hi> ſo it is ſaide, in the <hi>4</hi> of <hi>Wiſ. ve. <hi>10.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He pleaſed God, &amp; was beloued of him, ſo as, where he liued amongſt ſinners he tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated him, &amp; he was taken away; left wickedneſſe ſhould alter his vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, or deceit beguile his minde.</hi>
               </hi> But though it may be, that God ſometimes hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, in the taking of ſome of his children he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; yet I cannot ſee, but that both, the circumſtances of the place, and the very wordes of the tert, lead vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the other ſence here, then to this. Wherefore ſo vnderſtanding it, therby it is cleare, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet plainely vnderſtoode, that the taking away ſo many mercifull and righteous men, as hee ſaw then were taken hence indeede: was a moſt plaine deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crying, of a great iudgement, yea of ſuch a one, as for the greatneſſe and terribleneſſe thereof, was worthie not only to haue one face, but faces attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto it: to be faſt comming vppon that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whome the Lorde, bereaued of ſo worthie men. And that none coulde or woulde conceiue thus
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2583:18"/> much, he takes it to be an other ſpeciall and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proofe, of great ſenleſnes &amp; ſecurity in that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and therefore worthy to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained on: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where the like is found, there is the like collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be made thereof, &amp; it is by the Lords faithfull ſeruants, to be reproued, and complained of. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the better, either to preſerue vs, or to cure vs of this fault, let vs hereby learne this leſſon, when wee ſee the Lord, gleaning and gathering hence to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, many worthy men from amongſt vs, the world otherwiſe ouerflowing with great ſin and impiety, that then, the Lorde threattens vs, ſome very great iudgement or puniſhment, and therefore let it be, as a trumpet, blown in our eares from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to awake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs out of ſecurity, in ſin and vngodlines, that ſo, if it be poſſible, we may eſcape the ſame. And if this will not ſerue, to teach vs this leſſon. and to make vs take it out, conſider we but thus much further, that the Lorde hath giuen vs verie many moſt notable proofes, and examples, of the ſoundneſſe of the ground of this leſſon: For no ſooner had God gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to himſelfe, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the very children of <hi>Iacob, Ioſeph and the reſt,</hi> but as we read Exodus the firſt, <hi>there roſe vp a new king in Aegypt that knew not Ioſeph,</hi> that began mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly to tyrannyze ouer their poſterity, in which miſery, they continued euer after, for many yeares, as long as they continued in that countrey. And it was not long after, that God had taken hence, good
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2583:18"/> and godly king <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> er that this very euill here threatned, began to come vpon his kingdome, for (as ſome account) the <hi>4.</hi> yeare after his death, <hi>Nebuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adnezzer</hi> the great ſent by his father, <hi>beſigned Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and tooke Iehoiakim captiue, &amp; caried him and others with him captiue into Babylon 2. <hi>Cr. ca.</hi> 35.</hi> &amp; <hi>cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </hi> And before the laſt deſtruction of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and the vtter ſubuerſion therof, by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, the lord, as it appears in the Eccleſiaſtical ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries had gathered vnto himſelfe, al his Apoſtles, ſaue <hi>Iohn.</hi> And <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> writes, in the life of <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, that his city Hippo being beſiged, &amp; hauing bin, by the Va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dals, Goths, &amp; Hunnes, ſome 3.</hi> or <hi>4. months: ſome ten months before it was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, burnt &amp; conſumed, &amp; the people therof moſt cruelly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the Lord took him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in peace, by the means of an ague, which they tooke as a fearefull ſigne, of that, which followed, becauſe, as he wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the day that he fell ſicke, he made this praier vnto God, either to remoue the ſiege, or to giue the people hability to beare it out, or to take him thence in peace to himſelfe, before it ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>Cap.</hi> 28.</hi> &amp; <hi>29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea yet to preſſe this leſſon a little further, if in ſuch bad and dangerous times, the Lord alwaies go not ſo far, as quite to take his out of this life, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſome other ſort, call and ſeuere them out from the wicked, it portends, that ſome feareful euil is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening apace upon them. For when God had once
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2583:19"/> 
               <hi>ſhut vp Noe and his familie in the Arke, it was not long ere the floud came and deſtroyed the whole world beſide <hi>Gen. 7.</hi>
               </hi> and againe we read <hi>Gen. <hi>19. that the angels had no ſooner got Lot and his, out of Sodom, but it was deſtroied from heauen with fire and brimſtone.</hi>
               </hi> And it is not apparent, that God no ſooner had ſeuered vnder the conduct of <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, his people of Iſraell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Egyptians, that rather then an euill ſhould not come vpon them, they ran vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, &amp; ſo were moſt fearefully ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed vp of the red ſea, in following after that people <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.</hi> whereas of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary we ſee, howſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſins of the old world grieued god much in the meane time, that yet all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> while, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, <hi>for the ſpace of an 100, &amp; 20. yeares, that Noe by preaching and the Arke making, was calling them to repentance, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the windows of heauen were faſt ſhut, &amp; the floud could not breake in vpon the world of the vngodly <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.20.</hi> And we read that God told <hi>Abraham,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if there had bin <hi>but to, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Sodom, though the cry of their outragious ſins had pierced the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that yet for thoſe 10. ſake he would haue ſpared the city <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>ver.</hi> 32.</hi> yea we read in the next Chapter, <hi>Zoar was ſaued for Lot his ſake, &amp; he was willed to haſten thither for the Lord could do nothing to deſtroy the reſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was got ſafe thither, <hi>ver.</hi> 21.22.</hi> Yea y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is yet moſt of al to be noted, touching the preuention, of the particular iudgement here threatned. <hi>Ieremie,</hi> that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2583:19"/> propheſied in <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> time, <hi>is wild to runne vp and down Hieruſalem and to ſeeke &amp; enquire to and fro in the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtreets therof, to find out a man that executed iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſought the truth &amp; he is told by the Lord, that ſuch an one fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d there,</hi> he would ſpare it, <hi>Cap. <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </hi> And indeede Act <hi>27.</hi> we finde that <hi>275. ſoules that were in a ſhip with Paul, in a moſt dangerous tempeſt, eſcaped all ſafe to lande from the danger of ſhipwracke, for Pauls ſake that was in their company, <hi>ver.</hi> 24.</hi> &amp; <hi>44.</hi> O if the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wicked that here hate the godly, becauſe, <hi>their waies and thoughts are ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to theirs, &amp; as it were made to reproue theirs,</hi> as it is well noted wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome the <hi>2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</hi> &amp; <hi>15.</hi> &amp;c. had but grace to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and to remember theſe thinges. For then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, not onely hereby would they take occaſion, to be more thankfull vnto them, for all the good they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy whiles they liue with them, but alſo to account them ſo the pillers that keep vp from them the heatly iudgements of God that otherwiſe would fal vppon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; cruſh them to fitters, that when they were gon once, and taken from them, they could not but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with as with a milſtone be beaten to duſt and aſhes. For how can or may, any ſuch one, once imagine, God being as he is, at ſuch deteſtation with all ſinne, and knowing euen the moſt ſecreteſt alwaies as he doth, and beeing moſt able to puniſhe it as bee lift, that they in ſuch ſinnes as they ſecurely committe, coulde eſcape his hande one houre, if it were not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2583:20"/> more for the regard and ſakes of ſuch, then for their owne.</p>
            <p>And yet I haue not thus noted this, that the wick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed ſhould take any encouragement to continue in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie in this ſinne, as long as hee cauſee any godly men aliue in the countrey where he dwels: For they may goe on ſo long, and ſo far prouoke the wrath of the Lord againſt them, and the whole land for their ſakes, in deſpyſing all ordinary meanes, both ſweet and ſharpe, that the Lord ſends them to draw them to repentance by, as that the Lord may ſay vnto ſuch as he did afterwards by <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his <hi>15. <hi>Chapter. verſ.</hi> 1. though Moyſes and Samuel ſtoode before me, yet my affection could not bee towardes this people &amp;c.</hi> And after that againe by <hi>Ezechiel. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>ve.</hi> 14. Though theſe three men, Noe, Daniel, and Iob, were amongſt them, they ſhould deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſnes, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> And this his people to their ſmart, found moſt true by experience, for though they hadde as it is moſt cleare by the ſtories of thoſe times, and the writings of the Prophets <hi>Ieremy</hi> and <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> not onely them two, and <hi>Baruch,</hi> &amp; ſundry other very godly and vertuous men, when this euill began firſt to breake in vppon them, yet all theſe could not ſtay the Lord from executing his fierce wrath vppon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as you may ſee <hi>Ier. <hi>39.</hi>
               </hi> &amp; in the laſt of the Kings, &amp; Cronicles. And <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> gaue them the reaſon, why it could be no otherwiſe, ſaying, <hi>Cap. <hi>24.</hi> verſ, <hi>13.14.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2583:20"/> Thou remaineſt in thy filthineſſe and wickednes: becauſe I would haue purged thee and thou waſt not purged; thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthines till I haue cauſed my wrath, to light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thee. I the Lord haue ſpoken it: it ſhall come to paſſe, and I will doe it, I will not goe backe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I ſpare, neither will I repent. According to thy waies, and according to thy workes ſhall they iudge thee, ſaith the Lorde.</hi>
               </hi> Hee might well then ſay, that the Lord would haue purged them, and that they would not be purged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For <hi>what ſhoulde the Lord haue done to his vineyarde,</hi> which was that kingdome of theirs, <hi>that he had not done:</hi> as this our Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> moſt notably ſhewes them, <hi>Cap. <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>12</hi> &amp;c.</hi> He had beſtowed vppon them his holy woorde and lawe, he ceaſed not early nor late, no not when the iudgement was in ſight, to raiſe vp vnto them, moſt faithfull Prophets to tell them of their ſins, and to teach them how to preuent Gods iudgements, by true repentance: he gaue them very many good kings, and namely <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> euen a litle be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the appointed time for this euell, who was infe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rior to none that was before him, to purge the Church of al corruptions, and ſomtimes be thought to awaken them by forein wars, as in <hi>Afa</hi> his time, in <hi>Iehoſophats</hi> and <hi>Ezechias</hi> his raigne, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by dearth and famine, and ſometime by the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, and notably by the iudgement executed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their neighbour kingdome of <hi>Samaria:</hi> and yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2583:21"/> neither any of theſe, nor all theſe togither, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other good meanes, could cauſe them to ſhake of their ſenſeles ſecurity in ſin: &amp; therefore what ſhould the Lord doe elſe, but giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer, as he had threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the handes of that ſterce, cruell, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les nation, of the Babilonians?</p>
            <p>Now (welbeloued) you know the prouerbe, happy is he whom other mens harme may make to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and we know and are taught <hi>Rom. <hi>15.</hi> ver. <hi>4.</hi>
               </hi> that whatſoeuer thinges are written afore time are written for our learning: and therfore I aſſure you, we had neede to take theſe thinges to heart, and to learne in time to mourne for our ſinnes, and both to feele the preſent iudgement of God vppon vs alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in that of late we haue loſt by death, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy menne as wee haue, and to feare and tremble at that which this farther doth threaten vs. What meanes hath the Lorde omitted to winne vs to true repentaunce, that hee euer vſed to that people? Is not the light of his woorde ſhining now amongſt vs vnder the new teſtament, worthily in reſpect of the more lightſomenes thereof, vſually by <hi>Paul</hi> compared to the daie light, when as theirs in compariſon thereof, is called the night which is now paſte? and haue not we as many faithfull and painfull miniſters, thereby laboring to direct vs a right as ever they had? and hath not the Lorde beſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owed now of late ſundry princes, eſpecially her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, whom now we enioy (and I praie God long
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2583:21"/> may) vppon vs, very carefull to purge both the Church of corruptions, and the common weale of diſorders? And to goe on to the reſt, we cannot haue forgotten, but that by drough, dearth, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, we haue beene and yet are by the laſt, as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſummoned to repentaunce, as euer they were, and without warres we haue not quite bene: the Lord hath cauſed the earth, about ſome foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeare agoe fearefully to tremble and ſhake vnder vs, and now agaiue the ſatterday after this Noble Lorde Greye lefte this life, ſure I am in many places of this ſhire and ſomewhere elſe, it ſhooke as ſenſibly and terribly as before. And as for our neighbour countries rounde about vs, wee knowe and in ſome ſorte feele, that the heauie hande of GOD hath lien fore vppon ſome of them a great while. And wee haue founde, that ſuch hath beene the cankred malice of the curſed ſea of Rome, and of the confederates thereof againſt vs that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long time, by all treacherous deuiſes that they could inuent, they haue ſought to ſet vs togither by the eares amongſt our ſelues, and to queuch they care not howe, the light of our <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that is, to bereaue our dread and gratious Queene of her life. Finally as yet I hope, it is freſh in moſt of our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, howe when theſe enemies of ours ſaw, that by their ſecret practiſes, they coulde noe way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, the Lordes name for euer bee bleſſed for it: then they brake out into open hoſtilitie, firſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2583:22"/> in Ireland, and ſence in comming with a hudge and mighty navye, which they counted, &amp; therefore cald, inuincible, with a ful purpoſe to inuade our land, and to ſatiſfie their bloudthirſty mindes vppon vs. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede we muſt needes confeſſe, to the glory of God, that by the valiant worthy and faithfull ſeruice of this honourable Lord, whoſe body now lies here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, &amp; by gods bleſſing thereupon, their courage in Ireland was ſo puld downe, and their combseut, that neuer ſince any more of them haue had any hart, to giue any like attempt there again: and as for their nauy, the Lord of heauen, led it ſuch a proceſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our country, that moſt, both of the ſhippes and men, he hath ſcattered and confounded in the bottom of the ſea. Yet we may be ſure his malice that ſet them thus on worke againſt vs, is not ſo abated, but that when ſtrength is recouered, and fitter opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity eſpied, we ſhall taſt of it, if they can. Wherefore if all this notwithſtanding we will ſtill continue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and careles in ſinne and vngodlines with the Iewes, and ſo ioine with them in the cauſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke God in his wrath to bring a further euill vpon vs, what reaſon is there but that we ſhall, we cannot tell how ſoone, taſt as deepely of the ſame, ſome one way or other. He is the ſame God now that hee was then, and he can puniſh ſin as well in vs as in them, and there is no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world but that we ſhould thinke, if we be iumpe with them in ſin, wee ſhall be made iuſt and iumpe with them in the puniſhment
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2583:22"/> for the ſame. In the name of God therefore, let vs take heede, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, hearing Gods curſes be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt vs for out ſinnes; that <hi>wee bleſſe not our ſelues in our hearts; ſaying, wee ſhall haue peace, although we walke on ſtil according to the ſtubberneſſe of our hearts, ſo adding drunkennes to thirſt,</hi> as it pleaſeth God by <hi>Moyſes</hi> to ſpeake to his people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in that time, <hi>Deu. <hi>29.</hi> ver. <hi>19.</hi>
               </hi> For if wee ſhoulde doe ſo, in the woordes there im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately following the Lorde telleth vs what we ſhall ſurely truſt vnto, namely, <hi>that he will not be mercifull to any ſuch, But his wrath and ielouſie ſhall ſmoke againſt ſuch, and euery curſe written in the booke of the lawe ſhall light vppon them, and hee will put out their name from vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> Wherefore to conclude this part, let eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s learne to doe as <hi>Ieremi</hi> hath councelled vs, <hi>Lam. <hi>3.</hi> verſ. <hi>40.</hi>
               </hi> that is, <hi>ſearch and trye our waies and turne vnto the Lorde, lifting vp our handes and heartes vnto him in the heauens,</hi> for mercy to vs and out Lande, for as he faith in the twenty two verſe of that Chapter, our manifolde and great ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſidered, ſo we haue cauſe, to ſay alſo, <hi>it is the Lordes mercies that we bee not conſumed.</hi> And further, let <hi>Ezechiel</hi> teach vs this one leſſon more, that not onelye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee our ſelues, euerie one for his owne particuler muſt thus turne to God, from all our ſinnes; <hi>but that wee muſt cauſe others ſo to turne,</hi> or elſe he will not once promiſe vs <hi>that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2583:23"/> iniquitie ſhall not be our deſtruction <hi>Cap.</hi> 18, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30.</hi> For euery man is bound to do what lyeth in him, to draw on thoſe that any way by his vocation in Church, or common weal, he hath a charge of. And (but that I haſten to the conſolation) I ſhoulde here teach you, that this conuerſion of ours to God, muſt bee ſpeedy without procraſtination, conſtant without interruption, harty without diſſimulation, vniuerſal without exception, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble without oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet faithful without all diſtruſt or doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. For thus hath the word taught it ought to be, if we would haue it to be acceptable before the Lorde, to put of his iudgementes from vs, that otherwiſe by our ſinnes we haue deſerued. But let thus much ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſe touching the Prophets complaint, and the vſe, that wee are to make of it: and nowe let vs proceede to the comforte or conſolation that hee giues in theſe wordes of his.</p>
            <p>Wherin, as I haue ſaid, we are to conſider whom be comfortes, and therefore how he deſcribes them, &amp; then how he comforts them, and therefore what the comforts be that he ſets down for ſuch. He deſcribes them in general, to be every one that walketh before God; in the latter verſe, and in the former more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to be righteous or mercifull men: of theſe thinges therefore now orderly, as they are prepoſed let vs conſider. By walking by an vſuall Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore in the ſcriptures we are to vnderſtande li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and hauing our conuerſation, in which ſence,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2583:23"/> ſaith God to <hi>Abraham <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>ve.</hi> 1. walke before mee, and be thou vpright,</hi> that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot and haue thy conuerſation. And <hi>1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 9.</hi> by a like metaphore, the life of a Chriſtian, is compared, <hi>to the running of a race,</hi> the conſideration of which metaphors, may and ought, to teach vs, that as it is our dutie, according to Chriſtes counſail, <hi>Luk. <hi>13.24. to ſtriue to get into this way,</hi>
               </hi> wherein wee muſt walke, and run, and that betime; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cauſe it is written, <hi>Eccl. <hi>12.</hi> verſ. <hi>1. remember th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> creator in the daies of thy youth, whiles the euill daies comes not, nor the yeares approach wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them:</hi>
               </hi> ſo likewiſe, when wee are got in, that wee maie neither ſtande ſtill nor goe backe, but that we are to walke, and runne right forwarde, taking heede, that neither we run round about, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow of this ſide, now o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that. And therefore we haue a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t giuen vs. <hi>Heb. <hi>12.</hi> verſ. <hi>13.</hi>
               </hi> to <hi>make ſtraight ſteps vnto our feere,</hi> and there alſo we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arned, to <hi>take heede of al halting in this way, leſt ſo we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned out of the way.</hi> Thus therefore to walke, or to runne this race, importes, that therein there is ſome difficultie, and that there had neede bee good paynes taken thereabout. Whereuppon the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> in the foreſaide place to the <hi>Corint. <hi>9.</hi>
               </hi> hauing ſaide, <hi>ſo run that ye may obtaine:</hi> to prouoke vs not to think it much, though ſo to do, coſt vs ſome paines, he firſt tels vs, <hi>that they that ſtriue for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſteries, though they do it to obtain a corruptible crowne,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2583:24"/> yet abſtayne from all thinges that might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and then hee layes before vs to the ſame ende, his owne example, howe that hee, the better <hi>to runne this race, bett downe his own bodie, and brought it into ſubiection, <hi>verſe.</hi> 25.27.</hi> And <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes. <hi>12.</hi> verſe. <hi>1.</hi>
               </hi> moſt plainelye hee calles vppon vs, <hi>to caſt awaye euery thinge, that preſſeth downe, and the ſinne that hangeth ſo faſt on,</hi> and ſo then ſaith, <hi>let vs runne with patience the race that is ſet before vs &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore the difficultie hereof conſidered, we had need euery one, to runne vnto God for helpe in this caſe, ſaying, with <hi>Dauid, Oh that my wayes were directed to keepe thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, teach me O Lorde the way of thy ſtatutes, direct mee in the path of thy commandementes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.33.35.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe touching this our walking, ſeeing it muſt hee as I haue ſaide, or elſe it is not that, that heere the Prophet requires in thoſe whome hee woulde comforte; ſure wee maye bee, that there is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vs by GOD (who would haue vs to walke before him, that is ſo, that he may take pleaſure and delyte in our walking) ſome perfect rule, from which wee maye not decline, either to the right hande or left: and this ſurely is his owne reuealed will and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oorde. For that is an ancient rule of God in matter of his ſeruice, <hi>ye ſhall put nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the woorde which I commaunde you, neither ſhall yee take ought there from,</hi> as wee reade
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2583:24"/> 
               <hi>Deuteronomie. <hi>4.</hi> verſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </hi> and therefore ſaith he <hi>Eſay. <hi>8. To the Lawe and to the teſtimonie; if they ſpeake not according to this woorde, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> ver. <hi>20.</hi>
               </hi> And therfore euen <hi>kings, are commaunded by the Lorde, to reade in the booke of the Lorde, all dayes of their life. <hi>Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomie.</hi> 17.19.</hi> And <hi>Ioſua</hi> particularly, <hi>to meditate therein daye and night, that it might neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of his mouth, that he might obſerue and doe according to all thinges written therein, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer turning from the rule thereof, either to the right hande or lefte: <hi>Ioſua</hi>
               </hi> the firſt <hi>verſe. <hi>7.</hi> and <hi>8.</hi>
               </hi> And wee may bee ſure God is, at the ſame point ſtill, and euer will bee, and therefore both <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> the <hi>29. <hi>verſe.</hi> 13.</hi> and <hi>Matthew. <hi>15.</hi> verſe. <hi>9.</hi>
               </hi> as Chriſt hath alleadged it, wee may ſee, that both in the old teſtament, and newe, God hath counted them <hi>but vaine worſhippers, howe neare ſo euer they drawe vnto him in woordes, whoſe feare is taughte by the preceptes of menne, teaching for doctrine mens preceptes,</hi> all which kinde of worſhipping or ſeruing of God, <hi>Paule</hi> condemne vnder the name of <hi>will worſhippe, or voluntarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, though otherwiſe it carrie neuer ſuch ſhew of humbleneſſe of minde, and of not ſparing the body,</hi> as you may reade <hi>Coloſ. <hi>2.</hi> verſe. <hi>23.</hi>
               </hi> very will therefore hath <hi>Dauid</hi> taught vs, firſt, <hi>that a younge man may redreſſe his waie in taking heede therto according to Gods word:</hi> and after, that <hi>his worde
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2583:25"/> was a light vnto his path and a lanterne vnto his feete: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</hi> Wherupon afterward in the ſame Pſalme <hi>ver. <hi>133.</hi>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e makes this prayer vnto God ſaying, <hi>order my ſteps O Lorde, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy word, &amp; ſo no iniquity, ſhall haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer me.</hi> I ſay therfore vnto you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>S. Peter, as new borne babes, if ſo be you haue taſted howe bountifull the Lord is, deſire that milk,</hi> that is that inſtruction, to direct you in this walke, <hi>that is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, that commeth from the word, or is according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, for that wil <hi>Peeter</hi> onely warrant you to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is without deceit, ſound, &amp; good, <hi>1. <hi>ep.</hi> 2.2.</hi> And marke, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame <hi>S. Peter,</hi> tels the Chriſtians in his time, <hi>that they were by Chriſt redeemed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vaine conuerſation, receiued by the traditions of the fathers, 1. <hi>ep. Cap.</hi> 1.18.</hi> For thereby you maye perceiue, that walking, or conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be vaine that hath for the warrant of it, both fathers and their traditions; ſo can none that hath grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of the Lord. But then may ſome ſay, where is this word of God to be found, that al this while you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto vs, to be the onely ſound and ſafe rule to walke by? To this I anſwere, this treaſure &amp; pearle is onely to be found in the fielde of the Canonicall ſcriptures of the old and new teſtament, and therfore no where elſe to be ſought for. And therefore, as it may be obſerued, throughout al the newe teſtament, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, whither they were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm truth, to confute error, or to exhort to godlines,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2583:25"/> or to dehorte from the contrary, ſtill fetch their light and ground, from the ancient ſcriptures. And <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaking onely of the ſcriptures, which were written when <hi>Timothie</hi> was a childe, <hi>2. <hi>Timothie.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe.</hi> 15.</hi> ſaieth, <hi>that they were hable to make him wiſe to ſaluation,</hi> and after addeth, not onely that <hi>the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to improue, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe,</hi> but alſo ſo farre, <hi>as that euen thereby the man of God may bee abſolute, beeing made perfecte vnto all good woorkes.</hi> And it is euident by Chriſtes ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Iohn. <hi>5.</hi>
               </hi> vnto the Iewes, <hi>ſearch the ſcriptures, for in them yee thinke to haue eternall life, <hi>verſe.</hi> 39.</hi> that this was the common opinion of the Iewes of them, that they were ſufficient to direct them to ſaluation. Howe can we then thinke, but that nowe much more, the whole newe Teſtamente beeing ioyned vnto the former, contayning as it doeth both a moſt lightſome expoſition of the former, and alſo conſummating the ſame, wee haue cauſe ſo to account of them? Sure I am, whatſoeuer our late Romaniſtes thinke, and write to the contrary, becauſe if this principle bee once receaued, they knowe well enough, their opinions wherein wee ſtande againſt them, can no longer haue anie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, wee haue a number of vs moſt plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in Print ſhewed them &amp; the whole Church, that this was the opinion of all the Churches of Chriſt,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2583:26"/> and of all the learned fathers therein for <hi>600.</hi> years after Chriſt at leaſt. Indeede then, if we woulde haue them to bee and proue thus vnto vs; <hi>wee muſt ſearch them,</hi> as Chriſt hath commaunded Iohn <hi>5.</hi> and we haue need <hi>meditate therin day and night,</hi> as we haue heard Ioſua, for all the great buſines that otherwiſe he had, commanded to doe, and as we read it ſet downe for a Property of euery man that would be bleſſed, <hi>Pſal. <hi>1.2.</hi>
               </hi> And no other good meanes of hearing them opened vnto vs, by preaching, or anie way elſe, that we can come by, muſt bee neglected, but carefully and religiouſly vſed, and with all other means, hartye and often prayers vnto God in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility muſt be made, that it would pleaſe God, ſo by his ſpirit, the authour thereof, to inlighten our darke harts, that we may vnderſtand them aright. For this is <hi>to ſearch for wiſedome, that lies hid therin, as for ſiluer, and to ſearch for it as for treaſures, and to watch dayly at her gates, and to giue attenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at the poſts of her dores, as we are commanded to doe, <hi>prou.</hi> 2.4.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.33.</hi> and thus doing, if withall wee forget not with <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtill to crie vnto God, <hi>open my eies that I may ſee the wonders of thy Lawe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. ſo calling after knowledge and crying after vnderſtanding, as we are taught <hi>pro.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ,</hi> 3.</hi> then, and not elſe, we are there promiſed, <hi>that we ſhal vnderſtand the feare of the Lord, &amp; finde the knowledge of God, to direct vs aright in al our waies before the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.52.</hi> Moſt fearefull
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2583:26"/> are the examples that we haue in theſe ſcriptures, of Gods wrath breaking out againſt ſuch, as haue not in the ſeruice that they haue tendred him, firſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſet this rule before their eies; yea though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſeemed to haue neuer ſo deuout and good meanings therein. To this ende, to let paſſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, examples of groſſe idolaters, vppon whome, in moſt fierce maner, his wrath hath broken out, to the vtter deſtruction of them, &amp; their countries, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in often is recorded: who yet often would ſeeme, ſo feruent in ſeruing of God, after their faſhion, that they would ſpare no coſt, no not to ſacrifice their own ſonnes in the fire, let vs but conſider of three or foure, that fell out amongſt Gods owne people. Doe we not read <hi>Levit <hi>10.</hi>
               </hi> that <hi>Nadab &amp; Abihu offred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe with their cenſors, vpon ſtrange fire, which the Lorde had not commaunded them, and that therefore a fire went out before the Lord and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured them, ſo that they died before him? <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.2.</hi> And what other cauſe was there that the Lorde ſmote <hi>of the men of Beth-ſhemeſh, 5070<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men,</hi> but that of a fond affection, and blind deuotion, as it ſhould ſeeme, for ioy that it was come home, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and to ſee whether all were ſafe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, they looked into the Arke, contrary to the rule of the word Numb. <hi>4.</hi> giuen in that behalfe? Notable likewiſe in ſhewe, was the occaſion and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, that <hi>Saul</hi> had, both in his <hi>offring burnt offring,</hi> in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Samuel 1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. &amp; in his &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oples
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2583:27"/> ſparing the life of Agag, and ſome of his cattel <hi>ca.</hi> 15. <hi>ver:</hi> 15.</hi> but yet, becauſe in both theſe, he walked without direction and warrant from the word of the Lord, in both thoſe places immediatly vpon his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, we read, that he was told, <hi>he had done foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, &amp; that the Lord was ſo angry with him ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, that he ſhould leeſe his kingdome.</hi> But that which we read touching <hi>Dauids</hi> bringing home of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arke <hi>2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 6.</hi> &amp; <hi>1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 13.</hi> and alſo <hi>15.</hi> he being the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was, in my opinion, giues vs (how godly and wiſe ſoeuer we take our ſelues to be) moſt excellent war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to take heede how holy and good ſoeuer our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents be, yet in our walking before God, not to tread a ſtep, without light and warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from his word. For there it appeares, that the firſt time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he went about it, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulted not with this word which would haue told him, <hi>that it ſhould haue beene brought home only on Leuites ſhoulders <hi>Num.</hi> 4.</hi> &amp; therfore to his great diſcomfort, it fel out, that he ſeeking to bring it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home, <hi>vpon a new cart, that Vzzah putting but his hand to hold it, becauſe the oxen did ſhake it,</hi> though of neuer ſo good an intent alſo, yet lacking warrant therefore from hence, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did for the whole maner of his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>he was ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the lord with ſodein death. 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</hi> But the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time when he had learned to bring it home aright, he proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pered in his enterpriſe, &amp; brought it home with great ioy and triumph, as it appeares, <hi>1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.</hi> In what caſe then, be all thoſe that glory in nothing more, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2583:27"/> when they walke either directly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, or quite be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> direction of this word? Surely we muſt needs both ſay &amp; thinke, that the further they either run or walke, the more they are out of the way. And yet this is not only the walking of <hi>Turks</hi> &amp; <hi>Barbarians,</hi> but the common walking, wherein they moſt glorie that are of the ſuperſtitious ſynagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> (as if I might ſtande vppon that point, I could moſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſhewe,) and therefore their glory in the end, will be their ſhame.</p>
            <p>But to go on, in that the Prophet here deſcribes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom he would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, not by bare walking, but by <hi>walking before him,</hi> by that <hi>him,</hi> vnderſtanding euen God himſelf, foraſmuch as it is euident, that by that kind of phraſe, <hi>before him,</hi> it is ſtill the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcriptures, when they ſpeake of that which either is, or ſhould be in Gods children, to vnderſtand that they walk, or ſhould, without all hypocriſy: we are to learne, that it is not inough to walke ſo before men, that they can ſpy no fault in our walking, (for ſo far came the hypocrite <hi>Mat. <hi>22. in his walking, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnto, and ſitting at, the mariage feaſt,</hi>
               </hi> for vntill the maiſter of the feaſt came, he was not found of any of the gueſts to haue lackt his wedding garment, as it there appears:) but we muſt haue a care, if we would be of the number that he talkes of, to be anſwerable within, euen in the ſecret of our owne hearts, to the outward good ſhew we make. For wee know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his eies are ſo bright, &amp; piercing, <hi>that he looks eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2583:28"/> through our harts, and reines, &amp; that nothing can be hid from his fight. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 44.21.</hi> &amp; <hi>Iob. <hi>42.2.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to walke thus before God, two legges and feere are neceſſary, for there is no walking with one, and vnles alſo both be ſound, it is rather like to proue a halting, then any walking: the right leg and foote, is ſound religion, and a liuely and true faith groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereupon: the left, is a holy life and true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, in the continual practiſe whereof, it conſiſteth. Both theſe muſt go togither, for where either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſeuered from the other, there is nothing but hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſte or ſuperſtition. And therefore let a man be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo zealous and ſincere a profeſſor of the Goſpell and ſound religion, yet if we ſee him careles touching his life, we hold him to be but a carnal goſpeller, and that this his knowledge &amp; profeſſion makes his life and perſon, the more abominable before God. So on the other ſide, let one be neuer ſo curious &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of a good life, inſomuch that in that reſpect Chriſt might compare him to painted tombes, and cleare waſhen cuppes without, as he did the Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, yet if their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be vnfound, as the Pharaſies was, he will not ſticke to cry out againſt them, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be to you hypocrits, as he did againſt the ſcribes and Pharaſes <hi>Math. <hi>23.</hi>
               </hi> we ſay therefore to euery one, <hi>ſhew me thy faith by thy works, and I will ſhewe thee my faith by my works, <hi>I am.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</hi> For we hold &amp; teach, that it is no <hi>liuely faith, but a ſhadowe of faith, where good works accompany it not,</hi> with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2583:28"/> the ſame Apoſtle <hi>ver. <hi>20.</hi>
               </hi> But then we hold likewiſe, <hi>that loue which is the fulfilling of the lawe,</hi> &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſeth within the compaſſe of it, al good works, can neuer be, <hi>vnles firſt there be a liuely faith, for it pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceedes from a faith vnfeined, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</hi> But this faith is that, whereby in Chriſt Ieſus, we are ſurely, and fully, ſoly &amp; wholy, iuſtified, for <hi>hee is the author and finiſher of our faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</hi> and <hi>there is no other na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby cometh ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but his. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.</hi> &amp; the other ſerue to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy vſes, as namely, <hi>to make our light ſo ſhine before men that they ſeeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may glorify our father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as Chriſt hath taught <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>5.16.</hi>
               </hi> &amp; to make vs, <hi>known to be his diſciples. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.35.</hi> and as <hi>Peter</hi> hath taught vs, <hi>to certify vs of our election and calling 2. <hi>Epiſt. cap.</hi> 1.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude therefore this generall deſcription of the Prophet, of thoſe whom he would comfort, let vs marke, that euery one that thus walketh before God, he meanes to comfort: for he ſaith, <hi>euery one that walketh before him,</hi> as our interpreter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rendred it: but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withall marke, that yet he means, to comfort none but ſuch, as liuing, and dying, are founde thus walking. For it is not inough in this caſe to begin well and to go on, for a time, vnles wee perſeuere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the ende. <hi>For he that puts his hand to the plow, &amp; look<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> backe, is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eet for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62.</hi> and the promiſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus, <hi>he that endureth to the end he ſhal be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2583:29"/> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. be faithfull vnto the ende, and I will giue thee the crown of life. <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.10.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>S. Paul Philip. 3.</hi> is a moſt notable example vnto vs, in this: who though then, he had well ny run his race, and had out run very many, yet, that he might attaine happily vnto the end thereof, he proteſts, that <hi>he forgot that which he had left behinde him, and endeuoured himſelf, to that which was before, &amp; followed hard to the marke, that ſo hee might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> vſing a word that ſhews, y ſtill the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer he came to the race end, <hi>the more he bowed &amp; enforced himſelfe forwarde, and ſo he wiſheth as many as be perfect, to be minded. <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</hi> &amp;c. For as we read. <hi>Pſal. <hi>92.13.14. ſuch as be planted in the houſe of God, they ſhall flouriſh in the courtes of God, and ſuch ſhal bring forth fruit in their age, &amp; euen then, be fat &amp; floriſhing.</hi>
               </hi> The Prophet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to teach vs thus much, vſes this word, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>walketh,</hi> in ſuch a tenſe or time, in his owne language, as wherby it is wel known to the skilfull in that tongue, he noteth a continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their ſo wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, euen vnto the time, when God tooke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence. Let vs therefore ſtudy euery one of vs, to approue our ſelues thus qualified whiles wee are in ſtrength and liuing, that we may be found thus walking, ſick, weake, and dying. For it is a common prouerb, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis vita, finis ita,</hi> ſuch life, ſuch end, or death. And there is ſmal likelihood (ſure I am, it is not to be preſumed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2583:29"/> on) that he that hath not begun thus to walk before he come to his death bed, will there begin, &amp; there be found ſuch a one. For who is ſo ſimple, but he may eaſily conceiue, that it is moſt likely, that he that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth both God &amp; himſelfe, lyuing, ſhal be deſpiſed of God dying. We dare not, nor may not ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>vera &amp; ſeria poenitentia</hi> can be <hi>ſera,</hi> that is, that true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and earneſt can be too late: but yet I can tell you, that <hi>ſera penitentia,</hi> late repentance, may be ſuſpected often, whither it will proue <hi>ſeria &amp; vera,</hi> earneſt and true. And therefore the ſafeſt courſe is, whiles we haue wit and vnderſtanding, and whiles we haue ſtrength and vſe of our ſences, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times faile vs in extremity of ſicknes, to labour to be ſuch, as here he deſcribes.</p>
            <p>Thus now in generall, we haue heard howe the Prophet ſets forth them, for whom he hath comforts anone to tell vs of, both liuing &amp; dear: let vs therefore marke further, what in particuler, he cals ſuch. The words that he vſeth, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, are in the former verſe, and they are wel rendred by our interpreters, righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous &amp; merciful men. The waies therfore of the Lord in particuler, that they, that would walke before him aright, muſt walke in; are righteouſnes or iuſtice, &amp; mercy and compaſſion. Iuſtice with mercy, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with iuſtice therefore, muſt go hand in hand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for iuſtice without mercy, wil ſoone proue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and mercy without iuſtice, will vs quickely prooue but fooliſh pittie, that warre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Cittie a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2583:30"/> But when to ſhew the one, and to doe the at her, that muſt be learned of iudgement, which is in deed, the right moderatour, &amp; directour of both. where theſe <hi>3.</hi> concur in one, their iuſtice ſhall be ſhown in time and place, and ſo likewiſe mercy. All theſe in perfection are founde in God, and therfore ſaith <hi>Ieremy <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. 23.24. let not the wiſe manne reioice in his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, nor the rich man in his riches, but let him that glorieth glorie in this, that he vnderſtandeth and knoweth me,</hi> ſaith the Lorde, for I am <hi>the Lorde, that ſhew mercie, iudgement, and iuſtice, in the earth, for in theſe thinges, I delight.</hi> And ſurely we are like the children of ſuch a father, to doe what wee canne, to bee like our heauenlie father heerein: for hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes not onely, to approue himſelfe ſuch an one, in all his doinges; but that we alſo ſhoulde bee ſuch. And therefore by <hi>Hoſea <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>verſe.</hi> 5.</hi> in the time of the olde teſtament, when ſacrifices were in the greateſt and beſt eſtimation, he taught his people, <hi>that hee deſired mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo by compariſon: which ſentence, Chriſt wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes them to conſider that ſeemed to bee offended at the mercy, hee ſhewed publicanes, <hi>Matthew. <hi>9.13.</hi>
               </hi> And <hi>to doe iuſtice and iudgement.</hi> (ſo ioyning the other two together) ſaith <hi>Salomon <hi>Proverb.</hi> 21.3. is more acceptable to the Lorde then ſacrifice.</hi> And yet <hi>Michah. Cap. <hi>6.</hi> verſe. <hi>8,</hi>
               </hi> moſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to commend theſe vertues vnto vs, ſaith, <hi>he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2583:30"/> thee, O man, what the Lorde requireth of thee, ſurelie to doe iuſtlie and to loue mercy, and to humble thy ſelfe to walke with thy God.</hi> Al which places layde togither, doe teach vs three verie good leſſons, concerning this matter. The firſt is, that he that hath any care to walke, as he ought before God, hee muſt haue an eſpeciall care, amongeſt all other things, if not aboue all other things, to deale iuſtlie, and to ſhew mercy. He muſt therefore abhor all iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as extortion and oppreſſion, and all cruelty and merciles dealing: and think, how deuout, zealous, and and religious ſoeuer he ſeeme to be, that yet al is but vaine, without theſe. And to this purpoſe it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely ſaid of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> in my opinion, <hi>pure religion and vndefiled before God, is this, to viſite the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles and widdowes in their aduerſity</hi> (therein calling for mercy) <hi>&amp; to keep himſelfe vnſpotted of the world,</hi> therein likewiſe calling for righteouſnes and iuſtice. <hi>Cap. <hi>1.</hi> verſ. <hi>27.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond leſſon, is this, that they that would rightly ſhew both, that they loue iuſtice, and mercy: muſt learne to ioine iudgment withall. For through the want and lacke thereof, it was, that both <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſhewed mercy, when they ſhould rather haue done iuſtice, the one vpon <hi>Agag</hi> the King of the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekits, 1. <hi>Sam</hi> 15.</hi> and the other vpon <hi>Bennadad,</hi> the King of <hi>Aram, 1.</hi> Kings the <hi>20.</hi> and therfore the one for his labour was ſharpely reproued in the name of the Lord, by <hi>Samuell,</hi> and <hi>tolde that therefore his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2583:31"/> kingdome ſhould be taken from him, &amp; the other was met,</hi> &amp; told likewiſe, by an other Prophet of the Lord, that <hi>becauſe he had let that Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nadad eſcape with his life, whom he had appointed to death, &amp; therfore deliuered into his hands, that therfore his life ſhould go for his, &amp; his people for his,</hi> as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares at large in the ſaid places. For by this, who ſeeth not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though this their dealing, caried a ſhowe of mercy, that yet in the ſigh: of God, for that the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licious enemies of him and his people were ſaued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, when they might haue bin kild, &amp; ſo diſpatcht fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer endangering of any his people afterwards, and that to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt terror of the reſt, it was accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted no bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then plaine cruelty. Theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples therfore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, if a noble &amp; valiant Captaine, hauing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder his Prince, to gouerne &amp; to defend a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame enuaded by malicious forrein enimies, guided &amp; aſſiſted therin by treacherous, &amp; traiterous ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e borne wretches, &amp; the Lord hauing deliuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp into his hand, had he not need to take heede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for lack of ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iudgement, he ſhew not fooliſh pity vpon ſuch, vppon whom iuſtice only indeed, is to be done? Who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can but commend this honorable Lord, both for his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, iuſtice, &amp; mercy for his dealing as he did in this very caſe, with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the fort in <hi>Ireland?</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeing (as I haue learned both of himſelfe, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> report of others y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were there with him) neither any maner of promiſe that euer they could get of him, nor their own deſert, could any way put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any hope
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2583:31"/> of any better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they found. And beſides, ſeeing it is moſt certaine, that he neither had then, any ſhipping to ſend them away withall, nor might leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there behinde him to ſhift for themſelus, nor yet lead them away with him captiue, without apparant ſhew, not only of further danger to the whole country, but alſo of ineuitable perill to his own company, being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo few, and ſo weakned with long being abroad, &amp; being alſo ſo meanly victuailed as they were, only for them ſelues: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is moſt of al, hauing to paſſe home ſo many <hi>100.</hi> miles as they had, and moſt therof, moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerouſly through the cuntries of their friends, and their own enemies, how could he in any wiſedome or pollicy (vnles men would haue had him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to al nature &amp; iudgment, for ſhewing fooliſh pity vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch vnworthy wretches, cruelly &amp; childiſhly haue bazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both all the cuntry, and his own company alſo, to a further perill then they as yet had been in) doe any otherwiſe then he did? And the Lord be praiſed for it, though he were in that cuntrey but a ſhort time, by experience we haue found, the Lorde ſo bleſſed his iudgement, both in his doing iuſtice vpon them that deſerued no other, &amp; in ſhewing mercy towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to whom it was to be ſhewed indeed, that euer ſince we haue had greater quiet and peace there, then was of long time there before, or otherwiſe was likely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhould there haue had yet.</p>
            <p>The third leſſon, that wee haue in the places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoted, touching iuſtice and mercy, to learne
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2583:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:2583:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2583:33"/> 
               <hi>Michah</hi> hath taught vs, who though he require, that we ſhould doe iuſtly, and lowe mercy, yet he requires for al that, that they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue both theſe, ſhould humble themſelues, to walke before God. For though our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences witnes with vs, euen before God, that vnfei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nedly we haue ſtudied &amp; had a care to walke before men and him, ſo in iuſtice and mercy, with iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that we may as worthily be called righteous, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull men, as any that here, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of; yet we muſt learne of the ſame Prophet, not in a counterfet humility, but becauſe indeede, it is ſo, and we thinke ſo, in ſimplicity to ſay &amp; confeſſe: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iouſnes is compared with that it ſhould be, that <hi>al our righteouſnes is as filthy clouts, <hi>Cap.</hi> 64. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</hi> that ſo ſtill with <hi>Paul,</hi> our <hi>own righteouſnes, which wee haue framed in the beſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the law, we may indeed account of no force or valew to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy vs before god, that as he ſaith, we may be found of him, not hauing our own righteouſnes, which is of the lawe, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, euen the righteouſnes which is of GOD through faith.</hi> for though, the titles of iuſt, righteous, and perfect men, be attributed &amp; giuen to ſundry in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, yet we are not to take &amp; vnderſtand them, howſoeuer the papiſts &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e other pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſtical heads fondly doe, as ſpoken to ſhew that they were quite without ſin, and abſolutely &amp; fully kept the law. For what is more plaine in the ſcriptures, then that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſinners: And therfore ſaith <hi>Dauid, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 143. <hi>ve.</hi> 2.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2583:33"/> enter him into iudgement with thy ſeruant of or in thy fight, no man liuing ſhall be iuſtified:</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in an other. Pſalme, namely, <hi>1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>ver.</hi> 30.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith if <hi>thou, O lord, ſtreightly markeſt iniquities, who ſhal ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Solomon</hi> his ſon, moſt plainly faith, <hi>there is no man that ſinneth not, 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 8.46.</hi> &amp; therefore <hi>pro. <hi>20.</hi> ver. <hi>9.</hi> Eccle. <hi>7.22.</hi>
               </hi> he ſaith againe, <hi>who can ſay, I haue made my heart c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eane, I am void of ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Surely there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the earth, that doth good and ſinneth not.</hi> And the new teſtament is as flat in this point. For <hi>Rom. <hi>3.10.</hi>
               </hi> we read, that there is <hi>none righteous, no not one,</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> moſt plainly faith, that <hi>in many things we ſinne all, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.2.</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> likewiſe, as plainely, writeth, ſpeaking of ſuch as himſelfe then was, <hi>If we ſay we haue no ſinne we deceaue our ſelues, and there is no trueth in vs 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we doe but take a viewe of thoſe that in the ſcriptures are moſt honoured with the titles of iuſt and righteous men, wee ſhall finde the ſame ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, tell vs of ſome ſinnes, of the verie ſame men. For who are more commended, in the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for ſuch, then <hi>Noah, Abraham; Loth, Iob, Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Dauid, Aſa, Iehoſaphat, Ezechiah</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah?</hi> And yet read we not <hi>Gen. <hi>9. of Noahs drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes?</hi> Gen. <hi>12.</hi>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>20. of Abrahams twice cauſing Sara to diſſemble her being his wife, to the great peril of her chaſtity?</hi> and <hi>Geneſ. <hi>19. that Loth was firſt made drunke by his daughters, &amp; then therin
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2583:34"/> that he committed in inceſt with them both?</hi>
               </hi> And <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Aaron both of them, at the waters of ſtrife <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 20. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. are told by the Lord, becauſe they beleeued him not there, to ſactify him before the people, therfore they ſhould not bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land that he promiſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And as for <hi>Dauid,</hi> it is not only wel known, that he grieuouſly <hi>fell, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery and murder, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. &amp; in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring of the people, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.</hi> but alſo euen in the adminiſtring of iuſtice, <hi>in adiudging, through his too raſh credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the firſt and falſe information of treacherous and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bing Sibah, to him, the landes of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent maiſter Mephiboſeth:</hi> and yet when he ſaw the innocency of <hi>Mephiboſeth,</hi> we read not that euer he reuerſt this his vniuſt ſentence. <hi>2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.</hi> Likewiſe ſurely are their faultes euen regiſtred, of all the reſt, how much good ſoeuer otherwiſe bee reported of them. For of <hi>Aſa</hi> we read, that <hi>he was wroth with the ſeer, and put him in priſon, and moreouer that then he oppreſſed ſome of the people. 2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 16.10.</hi> And of <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> it appeares, <hi>that he made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity with wicked Ahab, and ioyned with him to helpe him in battell, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.</hi> for the which vpon his returne, he <hi>is ſharpely rebuked by Iehu the ſon of Hanani, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</hi> &amp;c. And after the miraculous victorie that God had giuen <hi>Ezechiel</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the army of <hi>Senacharib,</hi> it is recorded of him, <hi>that therefore, he rendred not the Lord thanks ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, but was lift vp in his heart, &amp; ſo wrath
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2583:34"/> came vpon him, &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iudah &amp; Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame: 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.35.</hi> Finally touching <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> his ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſheweth, that he came to his death <hi>by fighting againſt Pharao Necho King of AEgypt at Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giddo, contrarie to the perſuation (euen from the Lord, as the text ſaieth) that, that king gaue him. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if any thinke that it is otherwiſe now, with them that are commended for righteous men in the newe teſtament, they are much deceaued. For though it bee ſaide of <hi>Zachary</hi> the father of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, <hi>that he was a iuſt man before God, and that he walked in al the commandements and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Lord, without reprofe <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</hi> Yet after in the ſame Chapter verſe <hi>20.</hi> for his not beleuing the words of the Angel, touching his wiues bearing of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, <hi>he is ſtrooken dome, and ſo continued vntill the childe was borne.</hi> And if we go on, and conſider <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul,</hi> moſt famous amongſt the Apoſtles, though it cannot be denyes, but that they ſtudied to be righteous and very god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, and that then they had the ſpirite of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to enable them both to will well and to doe well, yet euen in reſpect of the time when they were ſuch, they are not found without fault or ſin. For <hi>Math. <hi>26.</hi>
               </hi> we read how ſhamefully. <hi>for feare, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter denied his maiſter:</hi> and that at <hi>Antioch,</hi> a good while after Chriſts aſcention, and therefore after the deſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>on of the holy ghoſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him and his fellows,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2583:35"/> 
               <hi>he behaued himſelfe ſo, that Paul therfore openly rebuked him there and charged him, that he was to be blamed, for his ſo dealing, for that by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, he conſtrained the Gentils, to doe like the Iewes: inſomuch, that other Iewes (as Paul repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it) diſſembled likewiſe with him, &amp; euen Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas, was brought into their diſſimulation alſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>ve.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> Now <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>7</hi> to the <hi>Romanes <hi>ve.</hi> 10.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> moſt plainly confeſſeth, of himſelfe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee had ſtriuen and laboured for the contrary to the vtmoſt be could, <hi>that he found a lawe in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, rebelling againſt the law of his minde, which before he cald the ſin that dwelt in him, whereby it came to paſſe, that ſometimes hee did that hee would not, and was led captiue vnto the Lawe of ſin,</hi> inſomuch that moſt lamentably he crieth out, &amp; ſaith, <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhal deliuer me, from this body of ſin and death?</hi> and to the <hi>Co. ep. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>12.</hi> ve. <hi>7.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he complaines of a pricke in his fleſh, which he cals the meſſenger of Sathan, that did buffet him, whereof he could not bee rid, though he beſought the lord thriſe that he might.</hi>
               </hi> Very well therefore in my opinion was it ſaid of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erom</hi> in his epiſtle to <hi>Cteſiphon,</hi> againſt Pelagius, who vſed to obiect many of theſe examples to proue, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be without ſin, becauſe many of theſe are ſaid, as you hard in the ſcriptures, to haue beene iuſt and righteous men: <hi>iuſti appellantur non quod omni vitio careant, ſed quod maiori parte vntutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2583:35"/> commendentur,</hi> that is, they are called iuſt men, not that they were without all fault, but that they were commended with the greater part of vertues. Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truely, and wel worth the reading is this epiſtle of <hi>Hieroms,</hi> both to the confutation of the old &amp; new Pelagians, that notwithſtanding the plain euidence of al that I haue ſaid, wil yet hold, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life haue in themſelues a perfect and abſolute righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, for not only doth he moſt plainly therein, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that as an <hi>opinion that in it containes the poiſon of al heretiques, &amp; taketh man out of man, &amp; holdeth him that is in the body, to be out of the body; but alſo to be contrary to al experience, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt or to come, and directly to rob Chriſt of his ſpeciall prerogatiue, which is, to be without ſin.</hi> And moſt ſharpely and briefly hee confutes all their chiefe arguments, and leaues them neuer a ſtarting hole, and in the end concludes that, <hi>haec hominibus ſola perfectio, ſi imperfectos ſe eſſe nouerint,</hi> this is mans only perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know himſelf to be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. But if it were a thing, that I might longer ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon, it were an eaſie matter to keepe you an whole houre, with golden ſentences and argumentes, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of this father and the reſt, moſt pregnant to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For I can aſſure you, neuer a one of the ancient learned fathers, but they are full and forcible againſt al Pelagians, and other heretiques whatſoeuer, to humble men alwaies in the ſight of their own w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is, and imperfection before God.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2583:36"/>
            <p>And doubtles (though they that hold the contrary, wil not ſee it) in the great wiſedome and prouidence of God, it is, that whiles we are here, we ſhoulde ſtill, doe what we canne, finde our ſelues compaſſed with infirmities, and encombred with ſin. For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſee the power and ſtrength of ſin, the better, to make vs thankefull vnto our God continually the more, for our ſweet ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, that clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs from all ſinne. Hereby, we are from daie to day, made the more weary of this world, where wee ſee this troubleſome battel with ſin wil not end, and ſo the more deſirous of an other, when we are ſure it ſhal. Hereby alſo in the mean time we haue occaſion, the better to ſhewe our faith, our patience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant feruentneſſe, in flying to God, for helpe and ſuccour: &amp; therby the Lord breeds in vs, many a good vertue, as humility mercifulnes and compaſſion, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, &amp; preſerues vs from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, foule vices, of pride, hard hartednes and conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of others. <hi>Paule</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, that the pricke in his fleſh, that wee hearde him eare while complaine of, was giuen him, leſt he ſhoulde be exalted out of meaſure, through the aboundance of reuelations. <hi>2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>ve.</hi> 7.</hi> Wherefore, as of the fleſh of vipers, there is made, as they ſaie, a notable counterpoyſon, ſo of the vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous remnantes and reliques of ſinne, God in his wiſedome, and by his power, makes vs a preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue againſt moſt daungerous ſinnes. And as the ſkilfull Chirurgian, that woulde heale his patients
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2583:36"/> wounde, throughly to the bottome, keepes it the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger open, ſo dealeth the Lorde with vs, in this caſe; that wee by this meanes, ſeeing the depth and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſneſſe of our wounde the longer, may ſeeke and finde, in Chriſt Ieſus, our onely ſoveraigne Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian and Phiſition in this caſe, a full, and perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. For it is he alone, <hi>who his owne ſelfe, bare our ſinnes in his bodie on the tree, that wee being deliuered from ſinne, ſhould liue in righteouſnes, and yet by whoſe ſtripes wee are healed 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24.</hi> And ſurely <hi>the Phariſee puft vp with a conceit of his owne righteouſneſſe, ſhall goe home, in his iudgement as he came, and the very Publican ſhal be rather iuſtified then hee, <hi>Luke.</hi> 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> And therefore hee <hi>calleth onely for the heauy loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and weary of that heauy loade, <hi>Mat</hi> 11.28, &amp; offers himſelfe to thoſe that thirſt after him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.37.38.</hi> For <hi>to whom ſhould the Lord haue an ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but to him that is of a broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trite ſpirit <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 66. <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</hi> And who wil bee at this point, but he that hath learned <hi>to humble himſelfe before his God,</hi> as <hi>Michah</hi> hath taught vs, when he hath walkt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, in iuſtice and mercy, the beſt he can.</p>
            <p>Thus therfore I hope ſufficiently, we haue heard opened, whom the Prophet here minded fo comforte wherfore theſe things thus premiſed, &amp; vnderſtoode, I dare &amp; do confidently aſſure my ſelf, that this noble perſon, whoſe body lieth here before vs, anone to bee buried, was ſuch a one, both generallie and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2583:37"/> as here the Prophet hath deſcribed: and I hope there are few or none here preſent, that knew him in deede, but as I haue gou on, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> point to point, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining &amp; explaining the Prophets deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue thought it to fit him. Howſoeuer, for my owne part, hauing known him, theſe <hi>14</hi> or <hi>15</hi> yeares, &amp; hauing had very neere &amp; familiar acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with him, tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the ſtate of his ſoule and minde, I am fullie of that mind, ſimply, &amp; without al flattery, either before God or man, that he was ſuch a one as here the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh of. Loth I am to enter into any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularizing of that which I am able to ſay, but vppon my own knowledge, to the proofe hereof; for I haue neither wit nor vtterance fit and meet to expreſſe the ſame withall, howbeit ſeeing it is a thing expected, (I know) at my handes, and without ſome iuſt note of vnkindenes I cannot ſtay here, knowing what I haue knowne: and that to the glory of God, and good example of ſome, it may be, that that which I ſhall ſpeake may proue, though it come neuer ſo ſhorte of that which he hath deſerued: giue me leaue a little to apply in particular, from ſtep to ſtep the Prophetes deſcription vnto him, Firſt therefore to begin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, euer ſince I knew him, he hath bin one careful, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to walke before God in righteouſnes and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, for any thing that euer I coulde perceiue. And therefore hauing learned, that thus to doe, he muſt haue his direction and light from the worde of God, conteyned in the Canonicall ſcriptuees, rightly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2583:37"/> I muſt needs proteſt, that I neuer knewe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his place, nor ſcarſe of any other, more carefull &amp; diligent, to vſe al ordinary means to attaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. For euen hence it hath come, and to this end it hath bin, that along time he hath moſt diligently red the ſcriptures, attentiuely heard them red, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon, both publikely and priuately, as oft as he could; and alſo ioyned therwith, not only the helps of ſerious meditation, conference of the learned that be met withal, and the reading of all good and learned books of controuerſies that he could come by; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo twiſe or thriſe a day he hath vſed along time moſt earneſt &amp; deuout inuocation of the name of God, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly betwixt God &amp; himſelfe (beſides publike prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers alſo in his houſe, twiſe a day co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually) for grace to vnderſtand the ſame, &amp; to liue accordingly. Thus to read of the ſcriptures beſids other books, <hi>8</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a day was his ordinary taſke: and hence it came that he was a religious and deuout keeper of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> both, conſecrating it wholly to publicke and priuate holy exerciſes: that he wonderfully reuerenced all learned honeſt and painefull miniſters, that he could be acquainted withall: and that hee reuerenced lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and learned men, as hee did. In this time, that I haue known him, euen for loue to learning, I haue known him, to haue bin at three ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Actes at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde,</hi> and there alwaies to haue bin a moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hearer of al exerciſes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning to the ending. And by theſe meanes it pleaſed God to bleſſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2583:38"/> him, with knowledge and vnderſtanding, that for his place (let no man be offended with my ſpeech) no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> both for matters of the Church and common weale alſo, was better able and more carefull to ſpeake, in time &amp; place then he. And as by theſe means he was enabled to make euery good ſhewe of Chriſtianity; both for life and religion: ſo ſurely therein he was no man pleaſer, or time ſeruer, neither hypocrite before God, nor diſſembler with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For al that knew him, knew, he was no gloſer nor flatterer, nor a man that would be drawn contrary to his conſcience and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to do any thing, though in the woorlde he might haue gained neuer ſo much thereby. Neuer knew I man more faſt and faithfull to his friend, more iuſt of his word and deede to friend and foe, and more plaine in all his dealing with one an other, without partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And though I am perſwaded, that God had given him great iudgment, when to ſhew iuſtice and when to ſhew mercy, &amp; I know, that he had ſuch a ſpecial care, to deal alwaies vprightly in both, that wittingly and wilfully he could not, nor woulde not offend his conſcience, in either: yet ſeeing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and infirmity, as he did, and finding thereby, by ſearching his owne waies, what might or had any way failed in himſelfe, walking in the beſt manner he could: therby he tooke occaſion, when he had walked before God in righteouſnes and mercifulnes, and in al other his good waies, to the vtmoſt of his power, to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble himſelfe before his God to anſwere the reſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2583:38"/> of <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> deſcription of thoſe whom here he woulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. For ſtil I haue found him the nearer he grew to his end; the more watchful and careful ouer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſtriuing with God by al good means to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fit for him, ſo that for theſe <hi>3</hi> or <hi>4</hi> laſt years of his life, he hath ſeemed to ſtudy and to deſire nothing more, then that God would giue him grace, ſo to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his daies, that he might apply his heart vnto wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which was <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſute vnto God for himſelf and his people <hi>Pſa. <hi>9.</hi> ve. <hi>12.</hi>
               </hi> And howſoeuer he could be ſtout enough, according to his place, &amp; but as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him, when had to deale with men: yet when he had to deale with God, either in ſickenes or health, I neuer knew a man that in woordes and behauiour, would cary himſelfe more ſubmiſly and reuerentlie, or that gaue better teſtimony, of a broken &amp; contrite hart before him. What the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould I ſay more? Brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly this, that being the man that others know he was beſides my ſelft: her Maieſty hath loſt of him a loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, louing, and moſt faithfull and good ſubiect, the ſtate hath loſt of him a ſtout valiaunt and renoumed Captaine, reuerented of all the enemies thereof, forreyne, or domeſtical, for feare; and of al the true friendes thereof, at home or abroade, for loue. The Church, hath loſt of him, here an Honorable member, for his owne parte: and many therein a louing Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tron his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try hath loſt of him an vpright Iuſtice, a good houſ-keeper, &amp; a very father in any thing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he might ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lawfully inſteed. And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2583:39"/> I for my own part, haue loſt of him the honorableſt &amp; moſt louing and faithfull patrone, that euer poore mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter of my condition loſt. Here yet is our comfort in all theſe loſſes, that we all haue thus loſt by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence; that he hath himſelfe (as we ſhal heare anone) loſt nothing, but that both he hath found God, and God hath fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him, and taken him from vs, that were not worthie of him, to ioine him with thoſe, for whom he himſelfe had thus fitted him. For as he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued honourably and Chriſtianly, ſo hath he died. For though he were ſicke, an <hi>18.</hi> daies, and therein had many ſharpe, long, and bitter fits, of his old diſeaſe the ſtone (as it was taken;) yet being with him from time to time, vnto the end, as I was; I neuer hearde any word of impatiency, thereby wrong from him: but ſtill, the more ſore his fits were, and his ſicknes grew, the more earneſt and holy prayers and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations came from him; inſomuch that he continued, praying, and calling vpon God, to take him hence vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to himſelfe in peace, to haue mercy vpon him for his Chriſt his ſake, &amp; to receaue his ſpirit, vntill the very laſt ghaſpe: only the mercies of God in Chriſt Ieſus promiſed, all the time of his ſicknes, as very often he proteſted, were his comfort, acknowledging ſtil, that but for them, he were a moſt miſerable wretch, &amp; yet they being ſuch as they were, he would neuer geue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer truſting in him, howſoeuec hee dealt with him. From the beginning of his ſicknes, it ſeemeth that he had receiued in himſelfe the ſentence of death and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2583:39"/> therefore after neuer minded wordly thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then needs muſt: his continuall praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and children was, that the Lord would bleſſe them; then (as it ſeemed by the maner of his ſpeech) thinking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould do wel inough, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> meanly ſooner he left them. Indeed to his eldeſt ſonne, kneeling by his bed ſide, &amp; crauing his bleſſing, (though then it was very painful for him to ſpeak) he g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e it moſt Chriſtianly thus, ſaying, my ſonne heare; heare &amp; feare the Lorde feruing him in holines and righteouſnes al the daies of thy life, and ſo thou ſhalt want no maner of thing that is good: &amp; for the reſt of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid, there were bleſſinges inough in ſtore, which he prayed the Lorde to beſtow vpon them. And to others weep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng about him, I remember well he ſaid, with ſet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, and ſtated voice, (and I hope I ſhal I neuer forget it) weepe not for me, but weepe for your owne ſins. And thus neuer ſatiſfying himſelfe, with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of himſelfe before God on the one ſide, in the ſight of his owne vnworthines, and yet ſhewing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other alwaies that he had a chereful hope, frely &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be ſaued for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake a loue, through his worthines; whiles both they about him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the reſt of the family below togither, were in powring forth their prayers to God for him, the <hi>14</hi> day of the laſt month of October, being the Lords day, he ended the day of reſt, or Sabboth, in falling into ſuch a ſleepe and reſt, that now for euery he ſhal keepe a perpetuall Sabb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lorde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd thus (wel beloued) yee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2583:40"/> haue hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> both of the life, &amp; death, of this Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Lord Grey, though nothing anſwerably to that which he deſerued, yet ſo far, and ſo much, as I truſt, I going on, now laſtly to lay before you the comfortes, that the Prophet hath here ſet downe for them, that he hath here deſcribed: of your ſelues, with out any further application of mine, you will thinke that hee had, and ſhall haue his part and portion therein.</p>
            <p>Wherfore herein to bee as briefe as I can: as I haue ſaid, either they are ſuch as either may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſuch dying; or ſuch, as they onely taſt of and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy when they be dead. And two comfortes here I obſerue ſtill to be giuen them, of each kinde. The firſt of the former ſort, is taken from the end that God hath in taking ſuch away, for their good; and is thus much in effect. Though the wicked ones in the woorlde liue in neuer ſuch iollity and ſecuritie, in all ſinne and impiety, triumphing and hartening themſelues the more in their courſe, becauſe ſuch is the ſtate of thoſe that walke before God in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercifulneſſe here ſometimes, that they, through the vnkindeneſſe of the woorlde, can neither enioy any ſound peace in minde, nor reſt in their beds, liuing in it: nor yet ſo dye in the end, but that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are put to ſome violent death by their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and perſecutors, or dye of ſome ſuch ſharpe and paineful ſickeneſſe, that the wicked thinke they haue cauſe to iudge them, as a ſorce that God loueth not,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2583:40"/> and therefore that are periſhed: yet indeede for all this, the Lorde loued them aliue, and of that loue of his, hath taken them away by death before the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill daie come, which he hath prepared for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the wicked and impenitent. Let the words and circumſtances of my text be wel ſcanned, and it wil euidently thereby appeare, that it was the Prophets meaning to miniſter &amp; giue this comfort. For though both immediatly before my text &amp; after, &amp; by the word <hi>periſheth,</hi> he plainly ſhews, that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the righteous are pickt out from amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the wicked they conceiue no better of it, &amp; in that there is no reſt or peace promiſed the godly herein, but after they be taken hence; it be more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſinuated that both their liues &amp; deathes are often in this world ful of tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet that they ſhoulde not be diſcouraged, either with that they feele themſelues; or with the doings &amp; ſayings of the other, the Prophet aſſureth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; merciful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that walketh before god, that he is taken he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of loue, to exempt him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he can take it to bee an argument of loue in a huſbandman, or ſhepheard, foreſeeing a ſtorme &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſt before, to gather into his barne his harueſt, or vnto ſome ſhelter his flocke of ſheepe, then hee hath cauſe ſo to thinke, of the Lordes calling and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him home, before the euell daie come. With this God comforted <hi>Abraham <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> For there, <hi>firſt hauing tolde him, that his ſeede ſhould ſerue, and be ill entreated in a ſtrang land
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2583:41"/> 400 yeares; after to comfort him he tells him, that yet he ſhould goe vnto his fathers in peace:</hi> and ſo he did, as we read, <hi>Gen. <hi>25.8.</hi>
               </hi> But <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that liued not long before this euell ſpoken of here bego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne to breake in vppon the kingdome of <hi>Iudah,</hi> is a moſt not able example heereof. For <hi>by Huldah the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiſſe he beeing firſt giuen certainly to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that it ſhould ſhortly be: yet from her, this word withall was ſent him to his comfort, that hee firſt ſhould be gathered vnto his fathers, and put into his graue in peace: and that ſo his eyes, ſhould not ſee, the euill that God would bring vpon that place and people, 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.</hi> Wherein doubtleſſe, they could not but take comfort, and be the willinger to die, when where, &amp; howſoeuer the Lord appointed. For who would not be glad to flee out of a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> old houſe before it fall about his eares? Who would not take comfort vpon the ſea, ſeing a great ſtorme comming, to get into ſome ſafe haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt? Who being in a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and knowing the way to be laid for paſſengers, to ſpoile and to deſtroy them, would not bee glad to take vppe his Inne before?</p>
            <p>And yet this is not ſo to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though it were here either ſaid, or ment, that alwaies God taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, al ſuch as he deſcribes, before the comming of ſuch an euell as here he ſpeakes of. For <hi>Ieremie</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who doubtles was ſuch a one, <hi>lyued to ſee this euell come vpon them, to the full:</hi> as it is euident, <hi>Ier. <hi>39.</hi>
               </hi> which was ſuch a griefe vnto him, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2583:41"/> he wrote his booke of Lamentations. And it is the common opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that <hi>Iohn</hi> that beloued Apoſtle of our Sauiour liued to ſee the final and laſt deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> and the temple, and the vtter ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſion of that kingdom of the Iews by the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Onely therfore thus are we to take it, that when in ſuch had times as this was that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of, it pleaſeth the Lord, thought thorough many tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, liuing, and in the end alſo by great pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ying, to take many ſuch a way, that then, howſoeuer the wicked conſter this, that moſt certainly it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the Lord, of ſinguler and ſpecial fauor toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and namely to take them away from euel to come.</p>
            <p>This therfore ſerueth, not only, mightely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the wicked and vngodly from all ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus dealing with his, and to teach them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, to refor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e their iudgementes, of the liues and deaths of ſuch as I haue ſufficiently ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before in handling the Prophets complaineth but alſo it ſerueth as forciblye, to comforte and chea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Godly in the middeſt of all their tribulations li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and paynes and tormentes dying. For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, they may perceiue, though their peace and reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reſerued, vntill they be taken hence by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: yet both before, and in their very death the Lorde ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſpeciall fauour and loue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let ſuch take al the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they are enforced to ſuffer lying as dying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2583:42"/> father, for their good; as meanes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them to their heade CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS heere, that heereafter elſe where, they may bee made conformable vnto him: and therefore euen ſo manie argumentes, of a better life reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for them in an other woorlde. For howſoeuer they cannot chuſe but for the preſent, to fleſhe and bloode bee grieuous; yet certainelye, as the Lorde v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them to his, they are his very good meanes, to to mortifie his children to this woorlde; that they way be the readier and willinger to departe hence, when be cals for them: and in his bande, they are but as his fire, and furnare to make his, pure gold; and as his fanne to make them cleane corne for his own vſe, and as his mill to grinde them, and ouen to bake them, to bee pure mainchet to ſerue his owne ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And in the very ſight of the woorlde, to the glorie of God, and the good example of others, they prooue but the ordinarie meanes to cauſe their faith, patience and conſtancie in cleauing faſt to God, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, and in calling the more earneſtly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, to appeare. Let not any man therfore, be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide, or diſcomforted, at tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s incident to the godly liuing, or at the painfulnes, or manner of their death ſo they die co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant in faith in the Lord. Indeed, <hi>Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> friends looking vpon the tribulations that hee had to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooke occaſion thereby, to iudge him to haue bin before but an hyprocrite, but they were not onely rightly withſtoode by Iob <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2583:42"/> in the ende God himſelfe, as it appeareth in the concluſion of that ſtory, tooke Iobes part againſt them.</hi> And <hi>Luk. <hi>13.</hi> ver.</hi> the firſt, we read, that <hi>ſome told Chriſt, how Pilate had mingled the blood of certain Galileans, with the blood of their ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but Chriſt perceiuing that in ſo doing they thought, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> therfore they might iudge thoſe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lileans, to the worſe then of any of the reſt, he tels them in ſo thinking they were deceiued: &amp; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe, if they ſhould think that thoſe 18, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the towre of Siloah fel, were greater ſinners the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that dwelt in Hieruſalem, he ſhews them, they were in an error;</hi> thereby teaching vs that we may not by theſe outward accidents &amp; occurrentes iudge. But notable to this our purpoſe is it, to conſiders, that though, as we haue heard <hi>2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.</hi> the Lord promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take <hi>Ioſiah</hi> hence in his fauour (and therefore we may be ſure he did ſo) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>yet he came to his death be a wound taken at Megiddo, in a battle againſt, the Lordes liking taken in hande, againſt Pharao Necho king of Aegypt,</hi> as it is ſhewed in the next Chapter. For heereby any man may ſee, that one, as deerely beloued of God, as <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſometimes may haue ſuch a death: and that therefore men are not to iudge them, not loued or regarded of God ſtreight, that haue painful &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what extraordinary meanes to bring them to their deaths. Hereunto alſo, wel ſerueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which wee read <hi>He. <hi>11.</hi> ve. <hi>35.</hi> &amp;c.</hi> For though it be euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that there
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2583:43"/> the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of ſuch, as both liued and died out of all queſtion the deare children of God, and ſo were taken hence in his fauour, yet he ſaith, <hi>ſome of them were rackt, ſome tried by mockings &amp; ſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gings, ſome by bonds and impriſonment, ſome were ſtoned, ſome hewn a ſunder, and ſome were ſlain with the ſword &amp;c.</hi> and yet he ſaith, <hi>the world was not worthy of them.</hi> For the ſimpleſt man that is, hereby may ſee, that men may be the deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and be alſo moſt dearely beloued of him, and yet haue many tribulations in this life, &amp; in the end alſo be taken away by ſome tormenting death. If it were not thus, we ſhould condemn al the Martyrs which are inumerable, that for the Lordes cauſe, haue endured both liuing, and dying, wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and torment. Wherefore ſeeing we are compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh <hi>Heb. <hi>12.1.</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>with ſo great a cloude of witneſſes, in this caſe, let vs run with patience the race that is ſet before vs, looking vnto Ieſus the authour &amp; finiſher of our faith,</hi> who as he there ſheweth, hath run this race before vs. For ſeeing in him our head, we ſee that found true which we reade <hi>Act. <hi>14.12.</hi>
               </hi> that <hi>by many tribulations we muſt enter into the kingdome of heauen,</hi> let not vs, that as members haue communion and vnion, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, thinke to get thither any other way. And yet let vs hold it, for all this, a moſt ſound principle, that is ſet downe <hi>Pſal. <hi>116.</hi> verſ. <hi>15.</hi>
               </hi> that is, that <hi>precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death (alwaies) of his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2583:43"/> ſaints,</hi> let that therefore be effectually prouided for, that we liue and die the Lords, in being ſuch, both li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and dying as here <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of, and then let vs be aſſured, whatſoeuer the vngodly thinke of vs either for our tribulations liuing, or for our paines in dying, that the Lord alwaies hath a loue and fauor to vs, firſt in making vs ready therby to go hence, and then in taking vs therby away from the euil to come.</p>
            <p>The other comfort, giuen here by the Prophet, that we may caſt of, and ſtrengthen our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dying, yet before we die, lies in the two Hebrewe words, that are here tranſlated periſheth and taken away. For howſoeuer, the wicked, vſing the former of theſe of the deathes of the righteous, thereby mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that they, when they are once dead, are ſo loſt and gone, that they ſhall neuer be found againe. Yet the vſe of the word in the Hebrewe tongue, As not alwaies to importe ſo much: For it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</hi> touching <hi>Sauls</hi> fathers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>which are ſaid were loſt; and yet in that Chapter, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares they were not ſo loſt but they were found, ſale and ſound againe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. and the thing loſt by one, and found by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n other <hi>Leuit.</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. is expreſſed by a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atiue thereof.</hi> And the other worde, vſed here by the Prophet in his owne tongue, is ſo rich in ſignification, as it is noted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the learned in that tongue, and as they make it eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the vſe of it in other places of the ſcripture, that is ſignifieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> take vp to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> away,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2583:44"/> but alſo to drawe backe againe, to receiue backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to one, to gather vp, or together, and to cure and heale: they being therefore here vſed by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, to expreſſe the death of the righteous by, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are therefore ſure they are fit for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in my opinion touching the death of ſuch, thereby wee may well learne, thus much; to the great comfort of all ſuch, both liuing, and dying, that howſoeuer the prophane <hi>Atheiſte</hi> and <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi> count death, to be, <hi>vltima linea rerum,</hi> the vtmoſt bound of all thinges, and therefore cry one to another, <hi>Ede, bibe, poſt mortem nulla volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> eate and drinke, for after death there is no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and therefore are likely enough to account ſuch men deade, ſo to be quite periſhed, that they ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be againe; yet in deede and trueth it is nothing ſo. But ſuch, though by death, the worlde and men liuing, haue loſt them; yet another, hath found them, that is, the Lord himſelfe; and therefore though by their death, hee hath quite taken them from vs, and conueied them cleane out of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the liuing here: yet he hath thereby, but gathered them vp and together, from amongſt the wicked, with whom they were mingled, &amp; amongſt whom, to their griefe, they were as ſcattred, whiles they were here; that ſo, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſent into the world, to doe him ſeruice for a time, and as it were to play a part on a ſcaffold that he had appointed them, he might draw backe againe, and take home againe to himſelfe that there he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2583:44"/> both cure their ſoules of all ſinne and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and thorowly heale their bodies, of al ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and diſeaſes, whereof, neither, could be free or cleare, as long as they were here. And, that death to the righteous is no other thing, but thus, the ſcriptures doe plainely and plentifully teach vs: for <hi>Eccle. <hi>12.</hi> verſ. <hi>7.</hi>
               </hi> when it comes, we are taught, <hi>that the body (which he there cals duſt,) returnes to the earth from whence it came, and the ſpirite to God that gaue it.</hi> And therfore <hi>Chriſt <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 46. and Stephen, according to his example, dying, <hi>Act.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 59. commend their ſpirits to God: and Paul counts death 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the godly, but a flitting out of his earthy tabernacle, to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in heauen prepared for is;</hi> and therefore ſaith, <hi>that he deſired to be looſed, and to be with Chriſt <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.23.</hi> And therefore theſe thinges, thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hereby a moſt notable comfort to remooue the terriblenes of death, is giuen vnto ſuch, as liue and die the Lordes: ſo, that theſe thinges remembred, we may well ſay with <hi>Cyprian de mortalitate,</hi> of ſuch; <hi>non amittuntur ſed praemittuntur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are not loſt, but ſent before:</hi> and againe, we may well ſaid with him, theſe thinges being thus, as moſt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are; that <hi>eius eſt mortem timere qui ad Chriſtum non vult ire, quod enim mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ortalitatem, morte tranſgred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nur, non eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed, tranſitur, &amp; quis non ad meliora feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that is, he only, hath cauſe to feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:2583:45"/> not go to Chriſt, for in that we die, by death we paſſe to immortality, it is therfore no diſpatch or ful end, but a paſſage; and who would not make haſt to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? And ſurely, the good remembrance of theſe two comforts, I am fully perſwaded, did ſo mightily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with this noble perſon, that they ſwallowed vp, and made him ſo Chriſtianly and comfortably to beare, what paines ſoeuer he felt that led him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as I haue ſhewed before. For from what foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine elſe, could his ſaying, weepe not for me, weepe not for me, come, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence: that he was fully per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded, that death ſhould be an aduantage vnto him whatſoeuer ſhould follow therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs. And his oft &amp; earneſt praying to God, to take him hence in peace, and requeſting others, as namely my ſelfe, that I would pray vnto him, that he would: for he was moſt willing to come vnto him, and therefore would not once ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e with him to the contrary: whence came it but from a certaine perſwaſion, that death ſhould bee no more vnto him, but as I haue ſhewed? and ſo a meanes to bring him, paſt all danger either of ſin or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eknes, <hi>to the city of the liuing God, the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Hieruſalem, and to the company of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable angels, and to the congregation of the firſt borne, which are written in heauen, &amp; to God the iudge of all, and to the ſpirites of iuſt and perfect men, &amp; to Ieſus the mediatour of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of that company, that hee is gone vnto, <hi>Heb. <hi>12.22.</hi> &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2583:45"/>
            <p>Wherfore, to our further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort concerning him, our ſelues, and all others, that ſhall liue and die ſuch as here the Prophet ſpeaks of, let vs now go on, and view the comforts that he giues and ſets down, to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertaine to ſuch, being once taken he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by death. His words are touching ſuch, as our interpreter hath ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred them, <hi>peace ſhall come, they ſhall reſt in their beds,</hi> but in my opinion, better according to the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, others tranſlate, <hi>he ſhall</hi> (meaning the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous) <hi>enter into peace, vppon peace, or in peace,</hi> for ſuch variety there is, <hi>and they</hi> (meaning ſuch) <hi>ſhall reſt in their beddes.</hi> The knitting of which words immediately with the former, touching their taking hence, ought to teach vs, that the comforts hereby deliuered, are ſuch; as that immediately vpon death, ſuch as the Prophet ſpeaketh of, enter into poſſeſſion and fruition of. And that the comfortes prepared for ſuch, come immediately and preſentlie vpon their death, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vſed by the Angell ſheweth <hi>Apoc. <hi>14.</hi> v. <hi>13.</hi>
               </hi> ſaying <hi>bleſſed are the dead, euen from the verie inſtant of their death, alwaies after</hi> (as that worde ſignifieth) <hi>that die in the Lorde, for they reſt from their labours, and their workes</hi> (hee ſaieth not any bodies elſe) <hi>followe them.</hi> Which we ſee confirmed to be ſo, by that which we reade <hi>Luk. <hi>16.22.</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Lazarus his being caried, immediately vppon his death into Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams boſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in that theſe two thinges are promiſed them,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2583:46"/> vppon their gathering hence by death and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and that as it is euident, to giue them therein better comfort to enioy theſe; peace, and reſt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately vpon their death, and diſſolution of body and ſoule, then euer they did before: vnles we might thinke that the ſpirite of GOD, that directed the Prophet to comfort ſuch, could not tell howe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them effectually and to the purpoſe; wee muſt needes thinke, that by peace and reſt, are meant, farre more excellent peace and reſt, then ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enioyed here. Yea they muſt needes importe, that before death come, they neuer had either peace or ioye, in compariſon. And yet it is well known, both by ſcripture and comfortable experience, that GOD giues ſuch both peace and reſt, in ſome good ſort and meaſure, whiles they are here. For it is written <hi>Romains <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>1. that the iuſtified by faith haue peace with God, though not ſuch as the world giueth, yet ſuch as that their heartes neede not bee troubled, or feare,</hi> Iohn. <hi>14.27. as Chriſt there hath promiſed. And this peace,</hi>
               </hi> I tell you <hi>Paul</hi> ſaieth, <hi>paſſeth all vnderſtanding, and preſerues the heart and minde in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</hi> And who knowes not, that it is written, that <hi>God giueth his beloued ſleepe or reſt, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 127. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</hi> And who of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the better to enable them, to ſerue the Lorde comfortably in their callinges, haue not founde theſe ſcriptures verified vppon them. Otherwiſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2583:46"/> ſurely, they could neuer be able, to beare the heate of the day, and labour in the Lordes vineyarde as they doe. And thus much in my minde, will the verie Hebrewe words, that are tranſlated peace, and to reſt, beare: for it is well known, of euery ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man in that tongue, that the firſt of them, is vſed of the Hebrewes not onely to ſignifie peace, but all proſperity, and that the Roote that it comes of, doth not onely ſignifie to be at peace and to pacify, but to be perfected and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mated. And as for the other word likewiſe, it doeth not onely ſignify to reſt, but ſoundly to reſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, whatſoeuer others haue thought. I am reſolute, that by the former, the Prophet ſettes downe the comforte that concernes the ſouls of the righteous immediately vpon their death, and by the other, that, which reſpects their bodies, vntill the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reſurrection. By this then we may perceiue that the ſoules of ſuch ſtreight enter poſſeſſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> far greater peace and ioy, then euer they had here; for elſe we muſt needes thinke, that the Prophet could not tell, how to comfort ſuch (which he being herein by the ſpirit of God directed to one, as doubtles he was) but once to thinke were blaſphemy. I ſay of purpoſe of far greater peace &amp; ioy, then euer they had here: for though I know, that this imports that their peace, is ſuch, as that the angell from heauen might iuſtly in reſpect thereof, <hi>thenceforth immediately for euer pronounce the bleſſed,</hi> as we haue heard,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2583:47"/> 
               <hi>Reuelations. <hi>14.</hi> ver. <hi>13.</hi>
               </hi> yea that it is ſuch as is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terable &amp; vnconceiueable of mortal man; yet I know there is a conſummation behind, to be accompliſhed at the laſt day in the generall reſurrection, and that the very Saints in heauen wiſh &amp; exſpect that as we may learne <hi>Revelation. <hi>6.</hi> verſ. <hi>10.</hi>
               </hi> for to teach vs ſo much, they that are there moſt ſafe vnder the ſhadow of <hi>their altar Chriſt,</hi> vpon whom whiles they liued, they offered all their ſpiritual ſacrifices: are brought in crying, <hi>how long Lord, holy &amp; true,</hi> doſt not thou <hi>auenge our bloode, on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> For how can it be otherwiſe, but, that that ſoule, that here hath faithfully ſerued the Lord in the body, muſt haue a deſire there, once in Gods good time, to haue this body ioyned with it in the reward aſwel as it was before, in taking the right courſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. And when this cometh to paſſe, which muſt one day (becauſe the truth of Gods promiſes in his ſonne muſt be fulfilled, and otherwiſe he cannot ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a perfect Sauiour both of the bodies and ſoules of his, and to haue had iuſt cauſe to take vnto him both the body &amp; ſoule of man, &amp; to ſuffer in both as he did:) then doubties there cannot bee but ſinne acceſſe of ioye and peace to the ſoules of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in the meane time departed. And yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whilſt, heereby wee are aſſured it is ſuch as I haue ſaide,</p>
            <p>Now touching the other comfort, which reſpects their bodies, it is ſaid here, <hi>they ſhall reſt in their
<pb facs="tcp:2583:47"/> beds.</hi> By their beds, the Prophet vnderſtands, the places where the Lord in his prouidence beſtowes their bodies, whatſoeuer thoſe places be, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately vpon death, vntill the generall reſurrection. For we may not be ſo ſuperſtitious, though it bee meete that conuenient and decent order bee taken &amp; kept for the buriall of the bodies of the dead (the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to nouriſh the hope of the reſurrection) in ſome fitte place, as to thinke that none is in poſſeſſion and fruition of this reſt, before their bodies be buried in Churchyarde or Church. For we finde it an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall thing in the Scriptures, immediately when men die, to ſay <hi>they fell a ſleepe,</hi> though yet they be not buried, and ſo, as ſoone as GOD hath taken the ſoule out of the bodie; ſo ſoone, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that be, and whatſoeuer afterwardes becomes of it, or bee done with it, be it throwen into the ſea, deuoured of wilde beaſtes, burnt to aſhes, buried or not buried; it is ſo couched <hi>in the bed</hi> that God hath made for it, that there it is fallen into ſuch a ſounde ſleepe and reſt, that vnles God meane extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to ſhewe his power, as he did <hi>when Moyſes and Elias appeared with Chriſt in the mount, when he was transfigured <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.</hi> or as when that was, that <hi>Matthewe</hi> writes of <hi>Chap. <hi>27. that graues ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and many of the bodies of the Saintes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe that ſlept, and went into the holie Citie and appeared vnto many,</hi>
               </hi> (which if hee pleaſe to doe to his they ſhall be ſure to finde no diſturbance
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2583:48"/> therby) it ſhall more quietly then euer it did here, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any feather bed, for neuer ſo ſhort a time take reſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>till the laſt day, when the generall reſurrection ſhall be <hi>1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.15.16.</hi> For here, doe what we can, to make our beds ſoft, and to get reſt; yet our ſleepes are ſubiect to many interruptions, &amp; troubleſome phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and dreames: but in theſe beds, we ſhall be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with none of theſe. This the ancient Grecians had an eie vnto, in calling the ordinary places for the buriall of the dead <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, ſleeping and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting places. This ſpeach therefore of the Prophet thus vnderſtoode, is full of comfort and conſolation. For it ſtrengtheneth and nouriſheth our hope of the reſurrection. For we all know, that is the end of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs to our bed chambers and beds, that there, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after we haue ſlept, we may riſe againe: and we ſee by experience, that though we lie down wearied and tired, yet after conuenient ſleepe, though it bee but for a night we commonly riſe, mightily refreſhed, as full of interruptions and troubleſome dreames, as our ſleepes are, vſually. How much more then, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this long, ſound, and quiet ſleepe, ſhould we hope, and bee perſwaded, that our bodies ſhall not onely riſe againe, but alſo be woonderfullie altered. This the Apoſtle <hi>Paul 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</hi> moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably teacheth vs wher he telleth vs, that <hi>at the laſt day, the trumpe ſhould blowe, &amp; our bodies, ſhall riſe (the which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were laid down, were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible; mortall and inglorious) immortall incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2583:48"/> &amp; glorious;</hi> yea &amp; which is more, <hi>that then our bodies, that ſlept in him, ſhal be made like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious body of our Lord and Sauiour by his mighty power, whereby he is able to ſubdue al things vnto himſelfe. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2.</hi> And therefore when we fal a ſleepe in theſe beds, we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly falling a ſleepe, yet ſay with <hi>Iob. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 25. I am ſure that my redeemer liueth, and though after this skin, wormes deſtroy this body, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh, euen with theſe ſame eies and no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To grow therefore towardes a concluſion, this being the meaning of the Prophet (as I haue plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed it was) by theſe his comfortes to teach vs thus much, concerning the deaths of the righteous, thereupon, all theſe thinges neceſſarily followe: that, man conſiſteth of a body and a ſoule; that the body is mortall, and yet ſhall riſe againe; that the ſoule is immortall; that there is no ſuch Purgatorie for the ſoules of anie of the righteous that are taken hence walking before GOD, as the Romaniſtes talke of: for that they immediately enter vppon, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a moſt ioyfull peace; that therefore they all goe ſtreight to heauen, and that they paſſe not their time betwixt this and the iudgement in a ſenſeles ſleepe, or not feeling of anie woe, (as ſome haue phanſied) but in a preſent and continuall fruition of exceeding ioy and peace: and laſtly that neither the bodies and ſoules of ſuch, walke and wander vppe and downe here in this worlde, nor are ſubiect to the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2583:49"/> malice of Sathan or witches to be fetcht againe, to preſent themſelues to be conſulted withall by the living, as fondly ſome ſuperſtitious people haue i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined; for neither of theſe can ſtand either with the peace, that the ſoule enters into, as the Prophet hath taught, immediately after death, or with the reſt that he ſaith, their bodies enioy in their beds. And therefore with the beſt learned both ancient and of late time, we are to be reſolued, that all appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and viſions to the contrary, except ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I excepted, are either very illuſions of Sathan himſelfe, ſo offring himſelfe to be ſeene, to breed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romous opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead; or elſe that they are but imagined onely, as we doe many thinges in our dreames, which yet then, are nothing ſo as we phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſied. All which points, but that I haue wearied you already, were worth the further ſtanding vpon, and I would indeed, but that I feare I haue beene too tedious already, open and confirme them further, to the full confutation both of all Atheiſts and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. But ſeeing they are ſuch, as I hope you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready rightly perſwaded of; and I haue my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in a ſermon which I haue preached at the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the late Right Honorable Lord of Bedford, which is in Print, ſufficiently further vrged them, let it ſuffice nowe, thus onely to haue ſhewed you howe this text confirmeth the ſame, thus briefely as I haue.</p>
            <p>And to make an end, in full hope that this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2583:49"/> man, whome honorably to bury wee are here at this time, both liuing, dying, and dead; hath had, hath, and euer ſhall haue, to his euerlaſting comfort, his part and portion, in all theſe comfortes; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with (becauſe I ſee you much diſcomforted, and many preſent I perceiue are full of ſorrowe, for the loſſe of ſo woorthy a man, as I haue ſhewed you there is iuſt cauſe) I beſeech you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort your ſelues, and comfort one an other. And to ad one other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto theſe, to comfort vs all withall; the Lords name be bleſſed for it, he hath left here behinde him, as you ſee, an honorable ſonne and heire, of whome we all haue iuſt cauſe to conceaue very good &amp; great hope, that er long, the very liuely image of his father in him, to the comfort of all his fathers friends, will be reviued: which the Lorde grant euen for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard (right honorable and welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) both the Prophets complaint and comfort, and by the former we haue beene taught, that when in bad and vngodly times, moſt worthy men drop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way apace, that it is a thing to be greeued at &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, if men yet continue and go on in ſecurity in ſin and impiety: For it is a iudgement of God, of it ſelfe to be taken to heart, of all ſortes of men, that they leaue behinde them; and it threattens a further euil to come vpon them, and therfore neither to take it to heart, nor to vnderſtande ſuch a further iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be threatned thereby; are certaine tokens of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2583:50"/> groſſe and intolerable ſecurity, and a fearefull prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtication, that ſome heauie iudgement haſtens on a pace: the conſideration whereof, I hope, euen by the multitude of heauy countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that I now behold, hath and will haue his due effect in many of vs to our good awakening and reformation, in this reſpect. And by the Prophets conſolation, we haue learned, that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts only appertaine to ſuch, as ſo walke before God, in righteouſnes and mercy, as we haue heard; and that to all ſuch they doe: and therefore to this honorable perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and laſtly, that ſuch dying, may comfort themſelues, that God alwaies taketh them away to a good end in his fauour, and namely in ſuch times as the Prophet ſpake of, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euill to come vpon others: and that death it ſelfe is no ſuch looſing of them, but that God ſtreight findes them, and takes them hence backe againe to himſelfe, gathering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp and together from amongſt the vngodly, which were not worthie of them, to ioyne them to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed company of the reſt of his Saintes in heauen; ſo curing and healing them of all diſeaſes both of bodie and ſoule. And thus they once gone hence, preſentlie and immediately, both in body and ſoule, they enter into better eſtate then euer they were in here; the ſoule into better peace and ioie; and the body, ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſt, whereſoeuer it be beſtowed, vntill the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reſurrection, in better maner then euer it did aliue. Which day when it comes, which we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tel how ſhortly it will be, both body and ſoule ſhall bee
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2583:50"/> ioyned together, and ſo appearing before. Chriſt the iudge of quicke and dead, heare the comfortable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, ſet downe <hi>Mat. <hi>25.34.</hi>
               </hi> for ſuch: come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my father, receaue the kingdome prepared for you before the foundations of the worlde were laide: Whereunto the Lorde happely bring vs all, euen for ſweete Ieſus ſake, to whom with the father and the Holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one euerlaſting God, be al honour, praiſe, and dominion now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Pag. <hi>8.</hi> l. <hi>18.</hi> for two read too. <hi>14. 27.</hi> for tyles read tytles. <hi>52. 2.</hi> for low. r. loue. <hi>54. 1.</hi> put out in. <hi>58. 12.</hi> for when, r. where. <hi>63. 10.</hi> for <hi>9.</hi> r. <hi>90. 77. 20.</hi> next vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell put in ſheweth. <hi>71. 8.</hi> put out of.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
